<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The epitome of man's duty being a discourse upon Mic. 6.8, where hypocritical people are briefly directed how to please God.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17198081</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17198081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1621:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The epitome of man's duty being a discourse upon Mic. 6.8, where hypocritical people are briefly directed how to please God.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Francis Tyton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly boudn, with print show-through and slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Micah VI, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106191:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106191:1"/>
            <p>THE EPITOME OF Mans Duty. BEING A Diſcourſe upon <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. where the Hypocritical people are briefly directed how to pleaſe God.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Qui in vitiis ſibi placent, non credent nobis, etiamſi Solem manibus geſtemus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lactant.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three Daggers in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> near the inward Temple Gate, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106191:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106191:2"/>
            <head>The Epitome of mans Duty.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MIC. 6.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>He hath ſhewed thee O man, what is good: and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT there are Laws of God engraven upon the tables of our hearts,
<note place="margin">Men would willingly pleaſe God and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too.</note> both the light of nature, and the holy Scriptures plainly tell us. Whenſoever we raze out or blot any of theſe Laws, we prick our conſciences, and draw blood of our own ſouls; and we become traytors alſo to Gods Majeſty, whoſe image and ſuperſcription we vilely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; and we know very well that we have incurred his high diſpleaſure. Now it hath been the enquiry of all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106191:3"/>men how to heal theſe wounds and gaſhes in the conſcience, and how to pacifie the wrath of God, and obtain reconciliation with him. Yet ſuch a love they have to their old traiterous practiſes which they are loth to leave, that they would willingly find a way to pleaſe God, and to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves both together. They will ſpare no coſt to be at peace with God, ſo it may not coſt them the life of their ſins, and they may ſtill be at peace with them. This is too manifeſt in the ſtory of <hi>Heathens, Jews,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Heathens</hi> knowing that they had offended their Gods,
<note place="margin">Appatent from the Heathens.</note> but having no mind to be perfect friends with them, invented all the wayes they could think of to get their good will, and obtain a grant of them to ſin and not be puniſhed, a licenſe to follow their own deſires without any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. This was the original of the multitude of Gods, of uncouth cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, horrid myſteries, Panick ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and affrightments: for they ſtood in a terrible dread that the Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106191:3"/>ſome miſchief to them which they knew they deſerved. The <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> (for example) worſhipped ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gods, who they thought might do them either good or harm: and leaſt there ſhould be any that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed no devotion unto, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might owe them a ſpite, they made an Altar to an <hi>unknown God.</hi> Or as we may gather from <hi>Diogenes Laer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> there being a great mortality among them, and they obtaining no eaſe by all their prayers and ſacrifices to the <hi>Gods</hi> of their own countrey, they imagined that it came from ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known hand, and ſo worſhipped that God whoſoever he was, that he might be reconciled to them.</p>
               <p>Juſt ſuch likewiſe was the humour of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From the Jews.</note> though better taught by God. They could contentedly beſtow any thing upon him, ſo that they might but have their own wills; And when their ſacrifices were coſtly and expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, they hoped God would be well ſatisfied; and account himſelf no loſer by their ſins which brought him in ſo many fat ſervices. And if theſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106191:4"/>would not give him full content, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then he ſhould not be ſatisfied, and rather then their ſins ſhould be ſacrificed, they would offer their own children unto him. They ask him if he would have their <hi>firſt born</hi> (as it was the manner of ſome heathens to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice men and women upon their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars to their Gods) If he deſired, the fatteſt and faireſt child in the flock ſhould be made an oblation to him; or if he would have all their eſtates evaporated in ſacrifices; all their riches ſmoak in his holy fires. It is the art of the <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> man to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God and fawn upon him; to bribe him (as it were) with a rich and gaudy worſhip at ſome ſeaſons, that he may have liberty at other times not to worſhip him nor ſerve him as he ought. And this being a timerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of ſoul, it makes the man very ſcrupulous how to pleaſe God, &amp; very laviſh in his expences, out of fear that he will otherwiſe be very trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to him if he be not pleaſed.</p>
               <p>There is ſtill the ſame diſeaſe in the ſoul of moſt that are called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And from the Chriſtians.</note>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106191:4"/>They know that they have ſinned, and that God is very angry; and they know that he is very powerfull and able to tear them in pieces: that he is a conſuming fire, &amp; can devour them in a moment; And this fear makes them ſigh and weep, knock their breaſts, and make a mournfull noiſe; faſt and pray, run from Church to Church, to offer him ſacrifice: hear Gods word and read it, or do any other thing but only do the will of God according to what they hear and read to be their duty. For they do not ſee any ſuch <hi>goodneſs</hi> in God that ſhould attract their love, and make delight in his life, and accord with his will; but they are only amazed at his <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and tremble to think of the evil that he can do them. They will give him (as it were) the <hi>fruit of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> they will pine and ſtarve their corps with faſting, if the doing that pennance will ſatisfie for their ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drunkenneſs, or for their greedy, ravenous, and devouring covetouſneſs. They will ſpare no <hi>ballowed breath,</hi> if their <hi>prayers</hi> may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106191:5"/>but blow away the infection of their oaths, lyes, corrupt communication that comes out of their mouths. If he will have a <hi>drink offering</hi> of their very tears, they will not grutch it, ſo be it that they may drown the tears of the oppreſſed, or waſh off the ſtains of cruelty and unmercifulneſs. They will mourn and lament; they will cry and houl upon their beds; they will ſigh and groan; they will walk heavily and ſadly; they will ſhut themſelves up from company; they will make large confeſſions of their offences; I cannot tell what it is that they will not do; but all is to intreat the Lord not to be angry with them for their rebellions: and if ever they commit the like again, they promiſe to make him as good an amends as they do now, and reſolve to faſt and mourn and bewail the fault; ſo that he ſhall not ſay, they did nothing to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon of all this is,
<note place="margin">The reaſon of mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to pleaſe him without leaving their ſins.</note> becauſe men love their ſins well themſelves; and think that God can love them alſo if he will, and that he need not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106191:5"/>be ſo offended and diſtaſted unleſs he pleaſe. They hope therefore that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey may intreat him to be more kind then to take away their beloved luſts from their embraces, ſeeing it is not his <hi>nature</hi> but only his <hi>imperious will</hi> (as they imagine) that ſets him ſo againſt them. And hence it is that they earneſtly begg his pardon for what his paſt: and for to incline him to condeſcend to their deſires of not being angry with their ſins, they are willing and ready alſo otherwiſe to gratifie him; and to give him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may pleaſe him as well as their forſaking of them. And at laſt by long uſe and practice they grow to this conceit, that they cannot imagine what God would have more then that they ſhould confeſs their ſins and be ſorry for them. And they live as if they could not deviſe what ſhould be more pleaſing to God, nor what he ſhould require further of mortal crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Whereas my text tells you plainly that it is the corruption of their wills rather then the weakneſs of their underſtanding, that makes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106191:6"/>them judge thus perverſly, For it is plain enough what is acceptable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, <hi>The Lord hath ſhewn thee o man what is good; and what elſe is it but to do juſtly?</hi> &amp;c. Thou needeſt not ask ſo many queſtions, (as they do, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7.) as if thou kneweſt not what God would have, nor what thou ſhouldſt do to him more then thou doſt, unleſs thou ſhouldſt offer thy children to him, or all the beaſts in thy paſtures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For a little inquiry will acquaint thee that God is very well pleaſed if thou wilt be juſt, mercifull, and humble.</p>
               <p>That ſeems to be the very true ſenſe and meaning of thoſe words foregoing,
<note place="margin">The ſenſe of the words from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on the foregoing.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherewithall ſhall I come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7. For this chapter contains the <hi>pleading of God</hi> with his people: in the <hi>firſt</hi> verſe of which he calls to the Prophet as his <hi>Attorney</hi> to manage his <hi>plea</hi> which he puts in againſt them. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the <hi>ſecond</hi> verſe calls for ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence whiles he pleads in open court in his behalf. After which in <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4, 5. he opens the caſe, and ſhews
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106191:6"/>how guilty they were even from their own <hi>confeſsion,</hi> that God had never given them any cauſe to be weary of his ſervice; but rather that he had done them all the good that they could deſire. And he leads their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories back as far as <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the wilderneſs, where his mercies were wonderfull to them, bidding them <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againſt him,</hi> and put in their plea alſo, if they had any thing to ſay in juſtification of their defection from him.</p>
               <p>Now in thoſe words, <hi>ver</hi> 6, 7. the Prophet ſeems to bring in the people interrupting of him in this complaint againſt them; ſaying for themſelves in a grumbling manner, <hi>What would you have us do?</hi> what is it that you would have us give to God? Do we not offer him ſacrifices, and bow our faces before his dwelling place? What would he have more then this? What better proviſion ſhall we make for him at his houſe? They ſpeak like men that knew not how to pleaſe God, and as if he was ſuch an one that no body knew what would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106191:7"/>him. Will he be pleaſed (ſay they) with a thouſand of rams? What, would he have all the ſheep in our flocks driven to his Altars? Would he have all the oyle in the land run in a ſtream to his houſe? or would he have our <hi>firſt born</hi> children now ſacrificed, which formerly we might exchange for ſome thing elſe? Would he have them in <hi>kind</hi> now offered up unto him? or would he have all the <hi>fruit of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> the blood of all our children one and other ſprinkled before him to expiate for our ſins? No, what need all this language (ſaith the Prophet here in my text) why, do you make your ſelves ſo ſtrange to what I ſay? As though you could not tell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all theſe aſperſions caſt upon God what he would have you to do? He hath ſhewed thee O man, who talk'ſt in this ſort, what is good; And tell me what thou thinkeſt in thy own conſcience it is that the Lord requires of thee. Is it any thing elſe but to <hi>do juſtly, to love mercy, and walk humbly with God?</hi> Their ſilence and not anſwering to the Queſtion argues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106191:7"/>that it is unanſwerable; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet goes on in the reſt of the chapter without any interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them, to lay open their ſins and puniſhments. It is not ſuch a difficult matter to pleaſe God as men make it; they know well enough what it is that he requires, if they have any mind to do it: and it is no ſuch ſtrange thing that they ſhould wonder he requires it at their hands.</p>
               <p>In the words you may obſerve theſe <hi>ſix</hi> things.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Six obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the words.</note> 
                  <hi>That there is ſome duty to be paid to God by every one of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That it is eaſie to know this duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That God exacts of man nothing in his duty which is unequal or unjuſt, and therefore it is eaſie alſo to do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>That a mans own conſcience will be witneſs againſt him if he do not perform this duty which God requires.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Juſtice, mercy and humble deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before God are the ſumm of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Theſe things were alwayes more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by God then ſacrifices, and other the moſt coſtly ſervices.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106191:8"/>
               <p>All theſe lie plainly before your eyes, as you may ſoon diſcern in the text: or they will all manifeſtly appear to him that will ſeriouſly attend theſe following conſiderations which I will offer to his thoughts upon every one of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>FOR the truth of the <hi>firſt, That there is ſomething owing by every one of us unto God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The proof of the firſt, from four things.</note> I need not ſearch all the <hi>divine writings</hi> to make out <hi>Gods title</hi> to mans duty; here are <hi>evidences</hi> enough for it within the compaſs of the text.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> he is our <hi>Lord</hi> [What doth the <hi>Lord</hi> require of thee?
<note n="1" place="margin">He <hi>is</hi> our <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </note>] and that by a title <hi>Paramount</hi> to all others. He gave us our being; and it is one of the <hi>Regalia</hi> of the crown of heaven, that all the <hi>Subjects</hi> of that kingdom are perfect <hi>creatures.</hi> We are all his vaſſals, and can no more be abſolved from <hi>fealty</hi> and <hi>homage</hi> to him, then we can ceaſe to be when we are. All the tenures, you know, among us were held by ſome <hi>ſervices:</hi> and that of <hi>pure Villenage</hi> made a man moſt at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106191:8"/>the will of the Lord: now ſuch is that which we owe to God, but more pure and abſolute then any other can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be. For our perſons are tyed and bound to him, and not only our ſervices; and we are not bound by our own conſent only, but we are <hi>Servi nati,</hi> born his ſervants; yea more then ſo, we are <hi>Servi creati</hi> (a title peculiar to him) <hi>created ſervants,</hi> who owe their whole ſelves to him.</p>
               <p>To deny therefore all obedience unto God, is to ſay, <hi>we are our own, who is LORD over us?</hi> It is the higheſt piece of pride and inſolency, an unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalleld rebellion againſt our natural Soveraign; a crime never to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned but by his infinite clemency, and our unſeigned ſubjection to him as long as we live.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">We are <hi>men.</hi>
                  </note> We are <hi>men</hi> [he hath ſhewed thee O <hi>Man</hi> what is good] and as we are reaſonable creatures, (1) We are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with more excellent powers of obeying God then other creatures: we are tyed to him in the moſt noble ſervices, and fitted for the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable employments. (2) And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106191:9"/>being reaſonable creatures, we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have a ſenſe above all others of our obligations to the ſupream <hi>Lord</hi> of the world; and our own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences give us the lye, if we ſay that we are free to do what we will. We know very well that when we took a being from him, we took an <hi>oath of faith and ſervice to him.</hi> There is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Hierocles.</note> as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then himſelf could ſay, an <hi>oath</hi> ineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenced and conſubſtantiated with man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; an <hi>oath</hi> of allegiance included in our very being; a <hi>Sacrament</hi> which we took to God in our mothers womb when we had firſt leave to become men. Our very reaſon and conſcience is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. (in <hi>Arrians</hi> Phraſe) that <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>engagement</hi> whereby we ſwear to God before we can ſpeak, as ſoon as a ſoul is breathed into us. He that breaks this ſacred oath or promiſe, doth unman himſelf as much as he can, and becomes unreaſonable. And (3.) as <hi>reaſonable</hi> likewiſe, a man can ſoon tell himſelf, that ſince he requires ſervice of perſons and things
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106191:9"/>
                  <hi>below</hi> him: he is much more bound in ſervice to the <hi>Moſt High</hi> who is the creator of us all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God <hi>requires</hi> ſomething of us,
<note n="3" place="margin">God makes demands.</note> which he would never do if it was not his due: He is not ſo <hi>unjuſt</hi> as to make demands where he hath no right: nor ſo <hi>needy</hi> as to beg that which is none of his own: nor ſo <hi>unkind</hi> as to follow us with continuall <hi>arreſts</hi> if we were his neighbours only, and not his tenants and debtors: nor ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe</hi> as to maintain <hi>officers</hi> and ſervants where he hath nothing to receive. Theſe are the words of the Prophet of God to men: now why ſhould God ſend his meſſengers and Miniſters, and call upon men ſo earneſtly, but that there are ſome ſervices incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, of which they ought to be highly ſenſible? What King makes proclamation where he expects no ſubjection? What Lord iſſues out commands, and ſends out his ſervants, where he hath no tenants that hold of him? It would be in vain to make ſuch loud cryes to men, if God expected nothing, but that men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106191:10"/>ſhould pleaſe themſelves, and do to him as they thought good. And it is too late to ask <hi>quo jure,</hi> by what right God <hi>requires</hi> our obedience: for I have already mentioned a title that comprehends all in it.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">The worſt of men confeſs his right.</note> The worſt of men confeſs his right. They that will not love him, will flatter him; they that will not give him all, will give him ſome: and they that have been negligent, ſeek to make him ſatisfaction. The Jews to whom the Prophet here ſpeaks, that would not do all his will, yet offer him large ſumms to buy off the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their faults. As they who are bound by their tenures to perſonal ſervice in the wars, would many times rather ſend their ſervant in their ſtead: ſo would theſe men gladly give God content by ſacrificing of their beaſts, when they had no mind to offer up themſelves. And all the wayes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the poor heathen ſtudy to make him reparation for their wrongs, and atone him to them, are plain confeſſions of this truth, that we owe ſomething to him.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106191:10"/>
               <p>In a matter ſo clear,
<note place="margin">Application, againſt the profeſſedly prophane.</note> I will not hold a candle to the Sun, but <hi>Firſt</hi> I ſhall rather wonder that there ſhould be any ſuch perſons in the world that live like bruites; as if God required nothing of them, but had made them to fill their bellies, and their purſes, and had given them leave not to be men. Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> they are (as the antient Scripture calls them) men under no yoke or government, unleſs it be the tyranny of their own luſts and paſſions, which domineer over them. Men that hate inſtruction and ſcorn reproof, as if we did them wrong when we tell them God <hi>requires</hi> that they ſhould be better. Men that lift up the noſe, like the <hi>wild Aſs</hi> in the wilderneſs which ſnuffs up the wind at her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſay, who ſhall command them? I wiſh there were no ſuch Monſters in the world, that ſhake off the government of God, and ſay of Chriſt, <hi>this man ſhall not reign over us:</hi> that take it ill to be touched in the tender intereſt of their ſins: that think (it is plain) neither God nor man can require more of them then they will give them.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106191:11"/>
               <p>Take heed that all this be not true in your lives, if not in the temper of your ſpirits. Remember ſeriouſly this fundamentall truth which you all know well enough already, <hi>That you are not at liberty:</hi> that there are ſome indiſpenſable duties he upon you: that you are tyed to God in the moſt ſacred bonds: and that it muſt be your greateſt care to ſee them well diſcharged.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly;
<note place="margin">And againſt pretended Saints.</note> if this be true, let the <hi>Libertines</hi> of this Age <hi>look to it,</hi> who think that all duty ſmells of baſeneſs and ſervitude (for by that name they have learnt to call all our ſervices) and that Chriſt came to free us from obedience to God himſelf. And let us <hi>look to them</hi> alſo: for if God muſt expect nothing from them, then what preſumption is it for us poor mortals to imagine that they muſt be juſt or faithful, or any thing elſe to us. And therefore you may obſerve, that at the ſame time that men began to think there was no obligation lay upon them of duty to God, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to imagine that all their Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106191:11"/>alſo were uſurpers, and that they had no rights but what the corruption of ancient times had given them.</p>
               <p>But Chriſt did not make us the leſs men, by making us to become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. He hath in his title the name of our <hi>Lord. Duty</hi> and <hi>true grace</hi> are it no ſuch difference as ſilly people imagine. Our obligations are not diminiſhed, but our ſtrength and power is increaſed; the ſervice is not altered, but <hi>love</hi> mixt with <hi>juſtice</hi> makes it more eaſie. We are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged from our work, but our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is ſwelled to an unmeaſurable diſproportion to it.</p>
               <p>But I paſs by this, becauſe I hope there are none that hear me, who ſet God and Chriſt at odds, and rob him of his <hi>creature</hi> under a pretence of making him a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE <hi>ſecond</hi> truth,
<note place="margin">The ſecond obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap> prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viz. That it is eafie for men to know their duty,</hi> is clear from two paſſages in the text. 1. The Lord hath <hi>ſhewed</hi> it to them. He hath demonſtrated it, &amp; made it very plaine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106191:12"/>ſo that if <hi>a Law</hi> do not bind till it be promulgated, that injures not Gods title at all; for he hath <hi>ſhewn</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed his mind. 2. It is ſo <hi>ſhewn,</hi> that men cannot but ſee it and take notice of it, as the <hi>manner</hi> of words by way of Queſtion doth clearly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, <hi>What doth the Lord require of thee?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid; thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt very well, I need not tell it thee, It is ſufficient only to put thee in mind of what thou art well acquainted with, even <hi>to do juſtly, to love mercy,</hi> &amp;c. And indeed it is ſo plain, that God <hi>ſhews</hi> it more wayes then one.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">God ſhews man his duty by his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> He <hi>ſhews</hi> it in our own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences by the light of reaſon. That the Queſtion ſuppoſes, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle expreſly ſaith, Rom. 1.19. <hi>Becauſe that which may be known of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in them, for God hath ſhewed it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</hi> Rom. 2.15. Which <hi>ſhew</hi> the work of the Law written in their hearts, their conſciences alſo bearing witneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (1) Mans ſoul doth not come out of Gods hand like a <hi>ſheet</hi> of <hi>white paper,</hi> in which there is nothing writ, or printed; but it is as a <hi>book</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106191:12"/>with many ſacred letters and divine characters. And (2) this book is not ſhut and claſpt, but it ſtands open to every ones ſearch. Nor (3) is Gods mind writ in ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the book, and wrapt up in leavs of darkneſs, but it ſhews it ſelf, and the letters are ſo great, that they will be read Nor (4) Is the ſence of this writing hard to be underſtood, but we call them <hi>Common notions, firſt principles</hi> which muſt be eaſie, and perſpicuous at the firſt ſight. Nor (5) need we go to the learned for their Comments upon them; or as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks, we need not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to a ſoul that hath been formed in the Schools, bred in a Library, and fed with Academical notions,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De teſt. Animae, cap.</hi> 1.</note> but <hi>ſimplex &amp; rudis, &amp; impolita, &amp; idiotica, illa ipſa de compito, de trivio, de textrino,</hi> the moſt ſimple and rude, the moſt impoliſhed and illiterate ſoul, the verieſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſoul; the ſoul that is bred in the ſhop or in the ſtreet, will teſtifie to theſe things, as well as that which is brought up in a Study, or learned retirements. Nor (6) is this book
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106191:13"/>ſo blotted by our fall into the dirt, but that the great lines of our duty are fair and legible. Juſt as we ſee the Sun in a cloud caſts forth a light whereby we diſcern in waht part of the heavens it is; or as a pearl will ſhine though it lie on a dunghil; ſo will theſe <hi>golden letters</hi> ſhine and gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in mens fouls, inan heap of rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh: and this light will break forth through a veil of darkneſs. And (7) where there are any <hi>lacunae,</hi> any gaps or breaches in a particular ſoul, by comparing all the <hi>Coppies,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with one anothers reaſons, we ſhould ſoon find the true ſenſe. Yea (8) more then this, it is not in the power of any of you to raze out theſe characters. They are not at your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to expunge or alter. For they are not ſo much <hi>ſcriptae</hi> as <hi>natae,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as born: we did not put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, but we find them in us. Though I might here cry out as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in another caſe, <hi>O anima naturaliter Chriſtiana!</hi> O ſoul, who naturally art a Chriſtian! yet let us look further and conſider,</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106191:13"/>
               <p n="2">2.
<note n="2" place="margin">By his word in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> That in the Bible God <hi>ſhews</hi> our duty more clearly by the light of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation. Here we are informed ſo exactly both what God is, and what man is: that he muſt be blind that doth not ſee that it is Gods word, and that mans obedience is due unto it. The very ſtile wherein it ſpeaks is, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> a form of ſpeech not to be found in other books. The contents of it about our duty are ſo clear and plain, that we may ſay with <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 6.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lex eſt lux, the Law is light.</hi> Or as it is ſaid in the viſion of <hi>Habak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuk,</hi> which God bid him write and make plain upon tables, (<hi>chap.</hi> 2.2.) he that runs may read it. And again theſe plain things are ſo agreeable to the connate principles of our mind, and the natural ſenſe that we have of goodneſs, that <hi>he hath put his laws in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts;</hi> and <hi>we need not ſay one to another</hi> (as if it was a ſtrange thing) <hi>know the Lord, for all of us may know him from the greateſt to the leaſt.</hi> In ſhort, this word is compared to a glaſs which ſhews unto us all our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106191:14"/>and repreſents unto us like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the face and image of God, whereby we ſhould dreſs and compoſe our ſelves to be beloved of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">By his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> He <hi>ſhews</hi> us our duty by his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the light of preaching. <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions,</hi> Iſa. 58.1. <hi>Wilt thou judge the bloody City? yet thou ſhalt ſhew her all her abominations,</hi> Ezek. 22.2. If there be any thing in this book, that is not ſo plain and clear: God hath ſet them to expound and unfold it. If any thing be dark, they are to manifeſt it. They open to men Gods word, and let them into the inwards and ſecrets of it. And by <hi>manifeſtation</hi> of the truth, they commend themſelves to every conſcience of man in the ſight of God, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. <hi>i e.</hi> men know in their conſciences that what we ſay in theſe matters, is the very truth of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note n="4" place="margin">By his Works.</note> The works of God in the world abundantly <hi>ſhew</hi> it by the light of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Thoſe <hi>exemplary puniſhments</hi> I mean upon notorious offenders,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106191:14"/>which ſpeak the finger of God; and his <hi>rewards</hi> to the righteous, which have many times no leſs of God in them. By theſe God vindicates his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and ſhews that he is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Governour; and that theſe are his Laws from which we ought by no means as we love our ſelves to ſwerve, or ſtir a foot. And ſo God ſaith, the <hi>wickedneſs of</hi> Judah <hi>was diſcovered, Ezek.</hi> 16.57. when he puniſhed her for her iniquity: It had often before been <hi>diſcovered</hi> by the preaching of the Prophets, but when that would not prevail, he laid it open in a more dreadfull manner by the voice of his judgements, which bid all men mind their duty better.</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">By the Church.</note> All the people and Church of God do <hi>ſhew</hi> it in the light of their lives. Their light ſhines before men;
<note place="margin">Math. 5.16. 1 Pet. 2.9.</note> they <hi>ſhew</hi> forth the praiſes or the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of him that hath called them out of darkneſs into his marvelous light. Men cannot but ſee that there are many in the world, that run not with them into the ſame exceſs of riot, that pray continually, that make a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106191:15"/>of every word they ſpeak; that are full of love and pitty; that are ready to do good; of a peaceable and meek diſpoſition, and ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe <hi>ſhew</hi> to men what is good, and they have them continually before their eyes. It is well if it be not ſo plain, that they become an <hi>eye-ſore</hi> to them: if they do not ſhine ſo bright in contradiction to their lives that they are offended at it. The Church of God is called the pillar and ground of truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. becauſe it doth hold forth the truth to men: and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it in the world, even as a pillar doth a proclamation which is affixed to it, ſo that all that paſs by may read it. And this it doth not only by preaching and outward profeſſion, but by the ſincere practice of a multitude of profeſſors. So that it is as eaſie for men to know their duty, as to know what a Kings proclamation is, which is not only cryed, but likewiſe poſted up in the market-place, that all may read it.</p>
               <p>Let us not then be ſo <hi>dull</hi> as to think on the one hand to plead <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106191:15"/>or <hi>weakneſs of parts,</hi> or <hi>inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncy of light</hi> in excuſe, for neglect of our duty: or ſo wild,
<note place="margin">We cannot then plead Ignorance, we need not be Seekers.</note> as on the other hand to turn <hi>Seekers</hi> in Religion, as though no body could yet find the way to heaven. The Lord hath <hi>ſhewed</hi> thee O man, what thou haſt to do; and therefore thou ſhalt not be able to pretend that thou wantedſt the means of knowledge, and hadſt no body to inform thee in thy duty: And he hath <hi>ſhewn</hi> it ſo long ago, that the world cannot be at this day to ſeek how to pleaſe God, as if no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy could tell what his mind was. To paſs by the former; let it be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning the latter, that they he ſhrewdly to be ſuſpected to believe no God; or elſe not to know what they mean by the name, who are to ſeek what Religion to be of. For no man can be rationally perſwaded of the being of a God, and not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he governs the world: And if he govern the world, it muſt be by Laws; And if thoſe Laws are incertain, they are no better then none. And if they be made for all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106191:16"/>his ſubjects, they muſt be plain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many of them underſtand but little.</p>
               <p>It is an eaſie thing to find what Gods will is, if we be but impreſſed with ſuch a ſenſe of our dependance on him as begets that reverence and fear of him, and that love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him, which eaſily and naturally flows from the ſenſe of our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. Gods mind is laid before us, we need only open our eyes and look no further. The way is plain, though it be narrow; the gate is open, though it be ſtrait. You may eaſier find the way then walk in it, you may ſooner ſee the gate then enter in at it. It is to be feared that they who ſeek for ſome new way, find this too ſtrait and narrow which they have been in; and they would have a greater liberty to themſelves, then formerly their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences durſt let them take. And then the Devil may ſoon ſhew them the way wherein they ſhould walk, and by a new light diſcover to them the paths of darkneſs. But I dare ſay if any man have a mind to live godly,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106191:16"/>to deny himſelf, to walk humbly with his God; he need not go to <hi>ſeek</hi> any further then this book. There he may behold ſo much to be practiſed, that if he will <hi>ſeek</hi> no further till he hath done that, I may warrant him from being of the number of any other <hi>ſeekers</hi> then thoſe that <hi>ſeek the Lord continually,</hi> that they may walk in all his commandments blameleſs. They are <hi>exceeding broad,</hi> they are to have an influence into the whole life: ſo that if the doing of thoſe be our end, we need ſeek for no more, for they will hold us at work all our dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE third obſervation is,
<note place="margin">The third obſervation proved.</note> 
                  <hi>That Gods demands are not unequall,</hi> or that he doth not exact of us any du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is hard and rigorous. They are not <hi>Draco</hi>'s Laws cruell and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall: nor the heavy yoke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> grievous, and painfull; but the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious commands of Jeſus Chriſt, the Laws that God himſelf lived by when he was in the fleſh: Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in germans to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106191:17"/>thoſe that rule in heaven. Two things in the text likewiſe ſpeak this, beſides that which is mainly intended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> the Prophet calls it <hi>Good</hi> which the Lord ſhews to us. He requires nothing that is for our harm, or our reall damage, or which a man ſhould refuſe if he was left to himſelf, did he rightly underſtand. And ſecondly, the queſtion likewiſe ſpeaks it, <hi>What doth the Lord require of thee?</hi> As if he ſhould have ſaid, what great matter doth he look for? what canſt thou except againſt it? is it any thing ſtrange and uncouth, that was never before heard of? Did thy mind ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give thee notice of it? Is it ſome monſtrous task, that the mind of man could never conceive it, nor think of it? No.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note n="1" place="margin">God exacts not things impoſſible.</note> God requires nothing <hi>impoſsible,</hi> as is apparent from two things which the text ſuggeſts to our thoughts. 1. He doth not bid men offer their children to him, which perhaps they have not. He doth not bid them buy them (as the Heathen ſometime were fain to do) for perhaps they are not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106191:17"/>able. He doth not exact of men (as the Prophet before ſaid) <hi>a thouſand rivers of oyl,</hi> which a whole Town or Countrey cannot afford: But as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>The commandment is not hid from thee; neither is afar off: It is not in heaven that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go up to heaven, and bring it to us, that we may hear it and do it? Neither is it beyond the ſea, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go over the ſea for us and bring it unto us that we may hear it and do it? But the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart, that thou maiſt do it.</hi> Deut. 30.11, 12, 13, 14. He doth not bid us all be Schollars, and underſtand all the books of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: He bids us not to climb up to heaven, and follow the chariot of the Sun, and track the paths wherein the Moon walks, and number all the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies, things which all mens parts and employments will not reach: but he ſaith plainly, <hi>do juſtly, love mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, walk humbly with God;</hi> things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, which we know well enough he requires of us. And ſecondly, you may obſerve that he ſaith, What doth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106191:18"/>the Lord require or <hi>thee</hi> O man? He doth not bid us make other men do juſtly and love mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He doth not command us to quell other mens paſſions, but our own: nor govern other mens deſires and luſts, but thoſe that are in our ſelves. He exacts not of us their duties, whether it be of our children or ſervants, or any ſuch impoſſible task, but our own duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God and them. When we have done what we can to make them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and do their duty, then ſaith the Scripture, God will not require their blood at our hand: But the ſoul that ſinneth, that ſhall die, and every ſoul ſhall bear its own iniquity.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Nor things unreaſonable.</note> He requires nothing <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> for he ſpeaks to us here in the Text as <hi>men.</hi> He bids us only love a greater good more then a leſs; a better thing more then a worſe; God more then the world; the ſoul more then the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. To do to others, as we would they ſhould do to us; to provide for a long life more then a ſhort; to lay up treaſure where none can take it away. He never bids us pray, unleſs we be in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106191:18"/>need; nor give thanks, but when we have received a bleſſing. Do but ſhow that you are not in perpetual want, and he will not ask you to <hi>pray without ceaſing;</hi> Do but make it good that you receive not innumerable bleſſings eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and he will not require you to give ſolemn and hearty thanks. Do but ſhew that it is better to be drunk then to be ſober, and you may take your fill; that a man can write better then God, and then you need not read his Word; that all time is your own, and then you may ſit at home, or recreate your ſelves on the Lords day. And ſo you may ſay of every other duty; not one of them is unreaſonable to be expected from us; for he commends the beſt things to us, and prefers a good to us before an evil; or a greater good before a leſs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nothing that is <hi>unnatural.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nor things unnatural.</note> I do not mean to corrupt nature; for ſo the moſt reaſonable thing that is may ſeem <hi>unnatural;</hi> as to provide for our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; to keep our word when it is to our damage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to nature as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106191:19"/>God made it, and to renewed nature, God requires nothing that is contrary. It cannot be unnatural to truſt God more then our riches; to live by faith in God; to depend upon his promiſes; yea to leave all for his ſake; and to truſt him with our lives, as well as our fortunes; to truſt him till another world, as well as in this. That which ſeems the hardeſt thing in Religion, is to lay down our lives if God call for them: to forſake every thing, rather then break the leaſt of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and yet there is nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural in it, but it is according to the right conſtitution and nature of our ſouls, to let him diſpoſe of our lives and goods, who gave them to us; to truſt him with them, and with our ſelves. It is not unnatural to give our lives to the God of Life; eſpecially ſince he hath promiſed a better life, which makes it infinitely reaſonable, and ſo far from being unnatural, that it is deſirable to do and ſuffer what he pleaſes.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in Epiſt.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nothing puts us ſo much out of all fear, as to ſtand in the fear of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106191:19"/>Laws. And nothing puts us in ſuch poſſeſſion of our ſelves, as to give our ſelves to him.</p>
               <p>But you muſt not think that when I ſay it is thus <hi>good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A caution.</note> there is nothing in it that is harſh and ſowre; for as the worſt things may be grateful, ſo the beſt things may be unſavoury to a bad palate. To the fleſh theſe things will not ſeem <hi>good</hi> till it be tamed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and then even the body will think it ſelf bettered by them. Many ſorts of poyſon are ſweet in the mouth, and many good medicines are as bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Many ſins are pleaſurable in the acting, though they be rank poyſon, bitterneſs and gall when they are gone down and ſwallowed into the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And on the contrary, many things are uneaſie and diſtaſtful, which afterward yield the rareſt delights, and the greateſt benefits. We muſt not think that our duty is ſuch, that we ſhall find no labour, no reluctance in it. No, it is not ſo eaſie as to eat our meat, or drink our drink; but being ſpiritual, it will find reſiſtance from the fleſh, and we muſt do ſome vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106191:20"/>to that at the firſt for our ſouls good. And then when we are uſed to our duty, it will be as natural to us as to eat; and though to put forth ſuch acts of obedience may not be ſo eaſie as to go to a feaſt, yet in the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they will be no leſs ſweet then our meat and drink.</p>
               <p>And if God require no unequal thing,
<note place="margin">No man then ſhall dare to plead his want of power to do Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</note> let no man think to plead his own <hi>inability,</hi> to do Gods commands. Why ſhould God give us a charge, if it were impoſſible to be kept? what good or wiſe maſter would require tasks that can never be performed? And beſides, is it not as poſſible to forbear ſin for Gods ſake, as out of reverence to a perſon whom thou fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt? Canſt thou not as well do what God commands, as what a friend en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns? Canſt thou not as well for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to be drunk, when none but God ſees, as thou canſt when the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Miniſter is in company? And if thou canſt be ſober to day, then why not to morrow alſo? If for a week thou canſt give thy ſelf to read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer, then why not for a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106191:20"/>moneth, and ſo for a year, and ſo for ever? If thou canſt be ſilent and hold thy tongue, why canſt thou not keep from Oaths and evil language when thou ſpeakeſt? And for other matters that are higher, if thou canſt do theſe lower even by an ordinary grace, why canſt thou not do them by the mighty power of Gods holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? If a man can abſtain from much evil by himſelf, then why ſhould he not be able to do good through God? There is no man ſhall have this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for himſelf at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he was unable to do what he knew; for then it will appear to all others and himſelf alſo, that he could have done more then he did. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired many things within himſelf; and for the reſt, the Spirit of God that moved him to them, would have aſſiſted him in them. Yea, even now it appears to mens own conſciences, that they can have no ſuch excuſe; for that is the fourth Obſervation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106191:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat mens own conſciences will ſpeak againſt them,
<note place="margin">The fourth obſervation proved.</note> if they do not what God requires.</hi> This is but a deduction from what hath been ſaid, and is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alſo ſuppoſed in the text. For <hi>firſt</hi> you have ſeen that men have a full knowledge of their duty. They need not be told it; but the Queſtion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being askt, it is ſuppoſed they can readily make an Anſwer. Or being named, it need not be proved, their own hearts inſtantly giving an aſſent. And therefore <hi>ſecondly,</hi> they muſt needs witneſs againſt themſelves: for as they know what they ought to do, ſo they know when they do not as they ought. And they know with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any information, ſo that if you do but ask the Queſtion, they are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently reproved of their negligence. And ſo <hi>thirdly,</hi> they will condemn themſelves; for it is contrary to the mind, to approve of that which it knows it ought not to have done. As it is a <hi>witneſs</hi> againſt it ſelf in matter of <hi>fact,</hi> ſo it will be a <hi>Judge,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106191:21"/>it ſelf as to matter of <hi>right.</hi> And this is a great deal more then the Devil can do againſt any man of us. For though he may inform and accuſe, yet he cannot ſentence or condemn. And if a mans own conſcience was clear, he need not fear all his plaints, all the bills that he is able to put in againſt him. But the conſcience is not only Informer, and Accuſer, and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but Judge alſo, and it ſentences and condemns us. And that <hi>firſt</hi> of all as unjuſt to God; and <hi>ſecondly</hi> falſe and cruel to our ſelves. For there was a debt owing unto God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we were unjuſt to him in not paying of it; and our own conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces told us of it, and therefore we were treacherous, falſe and barbarous unto our ſouls, in violating their light, and acting contrary to thoſe known principles that are within them. They will alwayes be telling us of it, they will laſh us with everlaſting torments, and after they have, being their own <hi>Judges,</hi> they will turn <hi>Executioners</hi> and <hi>Tortors</hi> likewiſe of themſelves. So that <hi>every wicked man is worſe then a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106191:22"/>Devil to himſelf,</hi> and he carries his own hell about with him.</p>
               <p>And therefore every one of us had need take heed how we render our ſelves guilty before God;
<note place="margin">The danger of ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our conſcience.</note> for he need but ſend to our own ſouls and rouze them up, and they will become our greateſt tormentors. As we ſet our ſelves againſt God, ſo will God ſet our ſelves againſt our ſelves. And as we are ready to impeach him of hardneſs and ſeverity, ſo ſhall we moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably indite our ſelves of cruelty and hard-heartedneſs to our own ſouls. And as we are apt to count him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable in his demands, ſo ſhall we accuſe our ſelves of unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and our ſouls ſhall fall out with themſelves as they did with him. Such a confuſion doth ſin make in the world, and in our ſelves. When we ceaſe to be friends with God, we ſhall never after be friends with our own ſouls. When peace is broken with heaven, all the world is diſturbed, and there is peace with nothing, no not with our own minds. Therefore as we love our ſelves, let us endeavour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106191:22"/>to live in all good conſcience before God. Let us not do the leaſt evil, for to avoid the ſuffering of the greateſt evil; and let us not neglect any good, for the purchaſing of the beſt good the world affords. Take the heathen mans counſel, which it is a ſhame Chriſtians ſhould not follow.
<q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.
<note place="margin">Chilo apud Laert.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Chuſe any loſs, rather then a diſhoneſt gain; for that will trouble thee once; but this for ever.</hi> It cannot be long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou feeleſt that <hi>occultum flagel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> that hidden whip, the cords of which thou art continually twiſting for to laſh thy ſelf; and though it ſcourge thee with a ſilent ſtroke which no body hears, yet it will make thee cry and roar in an eternal miſery. Then thou that wouldſt not <hi>do juſtly</hi> to others, ſhalt do juſtice upon thy ſelf; and thou that loved'ſt not mercy, ſhalt be able to ſhew none to thy ſelf; and thou that behaved'ſt thy ſelf proudly and contemptuouſly againſt God, ſhalt ſeem the vileſt creature in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106191:23"/>thy own eyes, and not have ſo much comfort, as to conceive a good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>But that all this which hath been thus briefly diſcourſed, may more fully and clearly manifeſt its truth, paſs we to the <hi>fifth</hi> obſervation, which is mainly intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>THat the duties which God requires of man,
<note place="margin">The fifth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</note> are, juſtice, mercy, and humble walking before him.</hi> Theſe three are the things which I ſay are ſo plain, ſo good, ſo neceſſarily incumbent upon us, that our conſciences cannot deny their obligation. Theſe are the <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dects</hi> that contain all the Laws where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are to live; or rather, they are the <hi>Breif,</hi> the <hi>Summary</hi> of all thoſe Laws. God hath at large delivered his mind, and ſhewn his will in the Bible; but ſometimes he doth <hi>epitomize</hi> it, and contracts the ſumme of our duty into a few commands, which are as it were the quinteſſence and heart of the whole. The Hebrew Doctors obſerve, that there are in the Law of <hi>Moſes,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106191:23"/>ſix handred and thirteen</hi> precepts. All theſe (ſay they) <hi>David</hi> comprehends in the compaſs of <hi>eleven, Pſalm</hi> 15.
<note place="margin">Our duty is ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a few heads in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> again brings them into a ſmaller compaſs, and reduces them to <hi>ſix</hi> heads, which you may read in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.15.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Gemara in Maccoth. cap.</hi> 3.</note> In <hi>Micah</hi> they are more compacted into <hi>three,</hi> naming this place which I am diſcourſing of. In <hi>Iſaiah</hi> again they are brought to two, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.1. <hi>Keep ye judgement, and do juſtice</hi> (though our Saviour hath better epitomized them, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and thy neighbour as thy ſelf</hi>) And then comes the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> and he thruſts all into one, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.4. <hi>Seek ye me, and ye ſhall live.</hi> But the Prophet <hi>Habakuk</hi> comes after and does it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (according to ſome of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſaying, <hi>The juſt ſhall live by faith, Hab.</hi> 2.4. which laſt place is much cited by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and you ſee what is the ſenſe of ſome of the Hebrews concerning it; that it is a compendious manner of ſpeaking, and includes in its comprehenſion all that which God ſpeaks in other places.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106191:24"/>Thus much <hi>falſe Chriſtians</hi> might learn of their enemies, that faith is not ſuch a lean and meagre thing as they make it, but is full of obedience to all Gods will. And according to this notion, I muſt look upon this part of my Text, as expreſſing in a few words, that which we muſt ſeek for at large in other parts of holy Writ, as repreſenting to us our whole duty toward God, and towards all men, yea and towards our ſelves alſo. For the opening of which, <hi>three</hi> things may be expected to be diſtinctly handled. 1. What it is to <hi>do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God.</hi> 2. That God requires theſe things of us. 3. That they are Good, and it is no unkindneſs in God to exact them. But for brevity ſake, I will do all theſe three together, and as I ſhew what is meant by <hi>doing juſtly,</hi> &amp;c. ſubjoyn ſome arguments for their being due to God, and likewiſe good to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106191:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>TO do juſtly,</hi>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">What it is to do juſtly.</note> is to give every one that which is his own. And it contains in it all the duties of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table,</hi> eſpecially of the <hi>eighth Commandment.</hi> Sometimes juſtice or righteouſneſs is taken <hi>largely</hi> for all Religion. Sometimes <hi>more ſtrictly</hi> for our duty toward our neighbour, as to matters of right. And ſometimes <hi>moſt ſtrictly,</hi> for the duties of the eighth Commandment, to defraud no man, to with-hold from none what we owe them; nor rob them, or take away from them that which they have in their poſſeſſion. And here it may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be taken in the ſtricteſt ſenſe, ſo that all the reſt of thoſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be included in the phraſe of <hi>walking humbly with God.</hi> But if it be extended to all of them, then by vertue of the <hi>fifth</hi> Commandment, <hi>to do juſtly,</hi> is to give our parents due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whether they be <hi>natural, civil</hi> or <hi>ſpiritual.</hi> And in reſpect of the <hi>ſixth,</hi> it is to preſerve the life of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and to have a care that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106191:25"/>him not in his being. In reference to the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> it is to preſerve his juſt relations, and not to touch them, or cauſe the violation of their faith to him. And in reference to the <hi>eighth,</hi> it is to preſerve his eſtate, and not meddle with his goods. And the <hi>ninth</hi> requires that we preſerve his good name, and not defame him, nor do any prejudice to his credit, no more then we would to his eſtate. And by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>tenth,</hi> we are to moderate our very deſires, ſo as not to envy to him that which is his, and long to have it in our poſſeſſion. And thus in General I may give you ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances of this part of our duty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That we muſt not <hi>with-hold</hi> from any man his due, if it be in our hands. Whether it be due by our <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or by his <hi>Labour;</hi> by his <hi>truſt</hi> repoſed in us, or by our <hi>offence</hi> againſt him; for we are bound in this laſt caſe to make ſatisfaction and reparation to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt not <hi>take</hi> from any man that which is his own, whether in his or any other mans poſſeſſion. Neither by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106191:25"/>our words, as through lying, falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor by our deeds, as ſtealing, robbing, or any other wayes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And we muſt not deſire or covet that which is another mans, nor look with an evil or greedy eye upon any thing that he enjoys. For this is <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> in our ſouls, as the other two are in our outward actions: and it is this baſe <hi>covetous</hi> and <hi>having</hi> diſpoſition, which makes men that they cannot forbear ſuch violent actions.</p>
               <p>Now how plain is all this to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<note place="margin">It is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of us.</note> and how meet is it to be done? What injuſtice do you find in God, for requiring juſtice at your hands? The very definition of this act, is to give to every one their due, or letting men have what is their own. And if it be reaſonable in others to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, then it is moſt reaſonably required of you towards them. And if you may demand it from them, and they from you, then much more may God demand it of you all. The rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is between us and others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it of us; and God made both
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106191:26"/>them and us, and thoſe relations; and therefore he may require this of thee, <hi>O man,</hi> whoſoever thou art. He doth but bid thee do what any heathen will tell thee is thy duty, if thou owneſt thy ſelf to be a man, and intendeſt to live among men, and not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed as a beaſt of prey. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> or any Lawgiver, could not call for leſs juſtice then God doth; only God requires it in words of greater force to engage us to it. It is well obſerved by a moſt learned Divine of our own,
<note place="margin">D. <hi>Saunderſon. Serm. in</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17.</note> that what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to give a man his own,</hi> the holy Apoſtle calls, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to render him his dues or debts.</hi> Both theſe words of the Apoſtle are more ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant then thoſe of the Philoſopher's, which may teach us that <hi>Chriſtianity requires under ſtricter bonds that which morality demands.</hi> For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a debt,</hi> or <hi>that which is owing,</hi> is more expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of our obligations then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>his own,</hi> or <hi>his property.</hi> We are debtors unto juſtice, and ſtand bound to our neighbours by our <hi>own act and deed,</hi> ſo that he may ſoon prove it is his own
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106191:26"/>which he requires. And then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to render</hi> or <hi>reſtore,</hi> is more full of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to give</hi> or <hi>diſtribute.</hi> For it ſignifies the <hi>returning</hi> of that which we have borrowed of our neighbour; and therefore he ſaith in the next verſe, <hi>Owe no man any thing,</hi> but to love one another. Every act of Juſtice is but the paying of what we have received; for he doth juſtice to us, and therefore we owe it back again to him. We do but pay him with his own coyn, and diſcharge that duty which not only God, but he hath obliged us unto. Not that it is lawful to cozen them that cozen us, and thus to render men as we receive; for that is but to be as diſhoneſt as they who would not pay us that debt which we took our ſelves to be bound in unto them. And there is a publick juſtice likewiſe to which we owe much; for it preſerves our eſtates, and from thence we look for ſatisfaction for our wrongs.</p>
               <p>And he is ſome ſavage wilde crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">And it is very good for us.</note> who ſees not all this to be <hi>good.</hi> For our neighbour, no queſtion, it is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106191:27"/>
                  <hi>good</hi> that we ſhould <hi>do juſtly;</hi> and if for him, then for us; for in his welfare, our own welfare conſiſts, we being both members of the ſame body; and in his honeſty is our ſafety. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that will not be honeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, would have all men elſe honeſt, and think that it is the beſt thing in the world that all ſhould deal juſtly with them. But how can any man expect that from another, which he will not vouchſafe to him? or by what reaſon is it that we muſt ingroſs all <hi>good</hi> to our ſelves, and let our neighbour have none of it? If we would have the monopoly of it, we ſhall never pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it, for men will deſtroy ſuch Wolves and Foxes that raven for themſelves, and do no good at all to others. Or if they do not ſpy their ſubtilty, but it is covered in darkneſs, God will tear the prey out of their mouthes, and the righteous Lord will make them know that it is <hi>bad</hi> to do unrighteouſly. For commonly we ſee that they who do wrong to others, are in themſelves or poſterity laid open to the violence of ſuch like unjuſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106191:27"/>And ſo the <hi>Eaſtern Fable</hi> taught the people, that the Woolf having ſoln a Pigg, was met withall by a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who took it away from him, and it was a wonder that he was not himſelf alſo torn in pieces. That which was not well gotten, could not well thrive; and men might conſider in the midſt of a violent act, that if they can find in their heart to be diſhoneſt, there may be others in the world of the ſame mind, that will make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce to deal with them as diſhoneſtly. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> am very much pleaſed therefore with the Northern proverb, <hi>That it is good ſport to be honeſt:</hi> The world may ſmile a while upon men in their diſhoneſt gain, and they may laugh at their good fortune;
<note place="margin">Job 20.5.</note> but <hi>the triumphing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the wicked is ſhort, and the joy of the hypocrite is but for a moment.</hi> If a man have but a little that is juſtly gotten, it is a great treaſure; for he <hi>gains</hi> a good conſcience, which will continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt him. But wickedneſs, though it be ſweet in the mouth, yet it is the gall of Aſps within: and beſides, the riches that ſuch a man ſwallows down,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106191:28"/>he ſhall vomit them up again:
<note place="margin">Job 20.12, 14, 15.</note> God ſhall caſt them out of his belly.</p>
               <p>And it is no leſs <hi>good</hi> for whole Nations,
<note place="margin">Good for whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, as well as for private men.</note> then it is for private men, to do juſtly; for they ſubſiſt by it, and it is the pillars of government, of peace and tranquillity. Every act of Juſtice is as a pin in a building, which joyns the parts of it faſter together, and maintains the intireneſs of the whole body. And when any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauds another, he pulls out a little pin, looſens the joynts, and doth what he can to bring all things to ruine. Either men become enemies to each other, and are in a ſtate of war when wrong is committed; or elſe they ſtand at a diſtance, and will have nothing to do with each other any more; and both wayes Society is diſſolved; that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which is the foundation of Common-wealths is over-turned.</p>
               <p>But ſee what the Scripture ſaith in all theſe caſes; where many bleſſings are promiſed to juſt men, and curſes are threatned upon all others, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.33. <hi>The curſe of the Lord is in the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106191:28"/>houſe of the wicked, but he bleſſeth the babitation of the juſt.</hi> A curſe indeed, enough to make a whole volume, for <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaw a flying roll, a ſheet of parchment as large as our Books, writ on both ſides with woes againſt the thieves and falſe ſwearers, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.3, 4. A place which I have taken notice of in the foregoing papers, and I will add by the way here, That a <hi>flying roll</hi> may not only denote the ſpeed which that Book full of curſes would make to come upon them; but alſo that the volume was open and ſpread forth, ſo that all might read it. For you know when a ſheet is not rouled up, but hangs expanded, it is moved by the wind, and flies as it were up and down in the air. Believe therefore the ſame wiſe man who ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.25. <hi>As the whirlwind paſſeth, ſo is the wicked no more: but the righteous is an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foundation.</hi> If you compare this verſe with the <hi>ſecond,</hi> it will ſeem like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that by a <hi>righteous</hi> man, he means one who <hi>doth juſtly,</hi> and thereby takes a courſe to ſettle himſelf; and by a <hi>wicked</hi> man, an oppreſſor, who may
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106191:29"/>ſoon loſe all that he hath unjuſtly got. Unrighteouſneſs you ſee will be our own loſs, more then any other mans; and therefore to do juſtly, is not more anothers <hi>good</hi> and <hi>gain,</hi> then it is our own. And ſo you may read, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.11. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34. where he ſhews the general concernment of Cities and Nations, of leſſer and greater Communities in righteous dealing. King <hi>Canutus</hi> knew this ſo well, that when he had condemned many male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, and one deſired it might be conſidered he was of the blood-royal, and have ſome favour: He ſaid, So he ſhall; let him be hanged upon an higher Gibbet. That Juſtice which he obſerved in puniſhments, if all would obſerve in their promiſes, Covenants, contracts, and all their dealings and intercourſes, they would baniſh ſuits, quarrels, wars and tumults out of the world. Peace would grow and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh on this root; and how great a <hi>good</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> we in this Nation by this time may have learnt. This would make our ſwords ruſty, and our armor good for nothing but to hang up in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106191:29"/>our houſes, and ſhew that we were once miſerable. All that the thunder and lightning of our Guns telleth us, is the worlds injuſtice, from which we muſt either be defended or delivered: Let this ceaſe, and they will all be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. This will put out the fires which nothing elſe will quench; and bury the enmities which elſe will alwayes be maintained. It was a wiſe and a true anſwer (with which I will conclude this) which <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> gave to one, who askt him whether <hi>Fortitude</hi> or <hi>Juſtice</hi> were the greater vertue, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>We ſhould have no need of your valour, if we were all juſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AS to <hi>do juſtly,</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">What it is to love merey.</note> is to give to men that which is <hi>their own;</hi> ſo to <hi>love mercy,</hi> is to give to others that which is <hi>our own.</hi> Or rather Juſtice <hi>renders,</hi> and mercy <hi>gives</hi> to men that which is their due. For that which is ours may be <hi>due</hi> to others who are in need, though not by mans Laws, yet by Gods. And there is a kind of <hi>Juſtice</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:106191:30"/>even in mercy, in ſo much that in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-language, <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifies giving of Alms, and a <hi>Juſt</hi> man, ſignifies one that is <hi>Good.</hi> But as theſe two ſtand diſtinguiſhed, <hi>juſtice</hi> requires that every man have his due; and <hi>mercy,</hi> that he have what is not by meer juſtice due to him. Three ſorts of men there are, ſay ſome of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Hebrews, and every one of them hath his peculiar ſaying. The <hi>firſt</hi> is the <hi>unjuſt,</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>That which is mine is mine, and that which is thine is mine.</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort is the <hi>juſt,</hi> and his ſaying is, <hi>That which is mine is mine, and that which is thine is thine.</hi> The <hi>third</hi> ſort is the <hi>good</hi> or <hi>merciful,</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>That which is thine is thine, and that which is mine is thine.</hi> He will not take away from others what is his, but give to them what is his own; and the Apoſtle is thought by ſome to allude to this diſtinction of men, when he ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Scarcely for a Righteous man will one die: yet peradventure for a good man ſome would even dare to die.</hi> I ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long this diſcourſe beyond its juſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106191:30"/>bounds, if I ſhould mention all the particular acts of mercy: Let it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice therefore in General to tell you,</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">We muſt not alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act our due.</note> That ſometimes we muſt let go our own right, and thoſe <hi>dues</hi> which in juſtice others are bound to pay unto us. Strict juſtice may ſometimes be a kind of injuſtice, <hi>i. e.</hi> it may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the ends of juſtice, which is preſerving of humane ſociety. And all will confeſs that it is ſo hard, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere and oppreſſive to the parties of whom it is exacted, that what <hi>mercy</hi> requires in this caſe, is very much like the demands of Juſtice. This bids us to make abatements ſometimes of what in ſtrictneſs we might ask; and to deal favourably and gently with all men. Where men have had great loſſes, and their eſtates are much bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, we muſt not hold them rigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to agreements. Neither muſt we take all advantages of our Brethren, nor ſeize on a mortgage when they cannot pay; nor ſue a bond, nor turn a man out of his leaſe, when he miſſes his day. And a thouſand ſuch like caſes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106191:31"/>there are, wherein mercy calls for that which is named kindneſs and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>But <hi>ſecondly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">We muſt give to others what they need.</note> as we muſt not alwayes require what is our own in other mens hands, ſo we muſt alwayes give to the poor what is in our own hands. We muſt relieve the diſtreſſed, defend the fatherleſs, plead the cauſe of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, viſit and help the ſick, deliver the priſoner and captive; and be ſo far from requiring in ſome caſes what others owe us; that we muſt give them more to ſupport their feeble eſtate withall. Many actions of <hi>mercy</hi> there are to mens ſouls, which I ſhall not mention, but in general tell you, that under this word are included all actions of Charity, pitty and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion toward our neighbour. And we muſt charge our ſelves with them, as we do with actions of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> And be as careful not to with-hold ſupplies from the poor, as we are not to ſteal: and not to ſay them nay when we are able, no more then we muſt lye to our Brother: and we muſt make proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for them, and do them good, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106191:31"/>as we watch over our ſelves, that we take not away from them, nor do them evil. The covetous is abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of God, as well as the thief; the unmerciful as well as the murderer. And therefore a man muſt not content himſelf that none can charge him with doing wrong: but his light muſt ſhine before men, and he muſt give Alms of ſuch things as he hath. And likewiſe he muſt deal fairly with all men, and not with a griping hand, and an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching head; and he muſt be ready to forgive all them that have treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed againſt him, and not hold them to over-ſtrict ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>There are many <hi>blind worldlings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Too many think it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to be juſt; but it is hard ſo to be, if we be not merciful.</note> many moles and earth-grubbers, that pudder and ſcrape in the earth all their dayes, and they do not invade any of their neighbours poſſeſſions, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach upon their ground, but content themſelves in their holes: and yet they do no good at all, nor bring any benefit to the world. They ſeem not ſo bad as rats, that eat our meat, and cloathes, and books; but yet none is the better for them: and at laſt many
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106191:32"/>are much the worſe. As the mole, though ſhe take nothing away from our ground, but ſeems to raiſe it higher; yet in time ſhe deſtroyes it all, by her hills which ſhe caſts up: So theſe men, though they do not plainly pick mens pockets, and rob them: though they raiſe fair houſes, and ſeem to make Towns more ſplendid where they live, yet they ſecretly work out all the old inhabitants, and make it all their own dwelling. They are as the ſpleen in the body, and draw all they can from others to fill their own bags; and the hard conditions which they hold men unto, with their obſtinate refuſal to relieve a decaying perſon, undoes many round about them.</p>
               <p>But that it is meet we ſhould do otherwayes, appears not only from that great rule of our Actions,
<note place="margin">God juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires mercy of us.</note> 
                  <hi>to do to others as we would they ſhould do to us,</hi> were their condition ours, and ours theirs: but alſo from the great merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of our God to us. We ſtand in need every day of Gods mercy, both in <hi>giving</hi> and <hi>forgiving,</hi> and why ſhould it be thought hard that he bids
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106191:32"/>us relieve the needy, when we our ſelves are in ſo much need, and he thinks not much to relieve us? But beſides, if it be hard for us to part with a little out of abundance; how hard is it to them, to want not only the abundance, but that little? And again, ſince God gives all to us, he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail it upon us and our heirs, on what conditions he pleaſes, and what great matter is it, if this be one, that we give ſome of it away to others? And truly this is one of the things that makes it <hi>good;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mercy is for our good.</note> for there is no ſuch way of ſaving and preſerving, as by giving: and no ſuch way of loſing, as by unmerciful ſaving. This cuts off the intail from many a fair eſtate, that the laſt Lord of it was a covetous miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wretch. And beſides, God bids us here <hi>love mercy,</hi> which we could not do if it were not <hi>Good.</hi> Neither will God tye us, as you heard, to ſuch hard conditions, as to delight in our own miſchief. And therefore all ingenuous heathens have counted it a piece of ſingular contentment to do good, and ſom looked upon it as a becoming <hi>little
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106191:33"/>gods</hi> in the world. This, if any thing, likewiſe, will draw the love and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others to us, not to ſay their perty adorations. A great light and ſplendor ſuch actions caſt abroad, when they are not done out of popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity and vain-glory, but out of love to mercy, and to God the father of mercies; and they get a man honour without deſiring of it, or taking any other pains to ſeek it. And there is not only <hi>pleaſure</hi> and <hi>credit</hi> in this noble vertue, but as much profit as heart can deſire. It muſt needs be <hi>good,</hi> becauſe it is called in Scripture <hi>doing of good;</hi> and though the phraſe properly imports the good of others, yet let me tell you, we hereby beſtow no ſmall boons upon our ſelves. God ſo loves it, that he loves thoſe that love it, and hath promiſed great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to them and theirs, in this world, and in the world to come. <hi>With the merciful, he will ſhew himſelf merciful,</hi> Pſalm 18.25. <hi>Bleſſed are the merciful, for they ſhall obtain mercy,</hi> Mat. 5.7. <hi>There is that ſcattereth, and yet increaſeth: The liberal ſoul ſhall
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106191:33"/>be made fat; and he that watereth ſhall be watered alſo himſelf,</hi> Prov. 11.25, 26. <hi>His righteouſneſs endureth for ever, his born ſhall be exalted with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> Pſalm 112.9. This is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon which I might dilate till night: For there are no leſs treaſures for the merciful man, then the rich man hath of wealth in his houſe; yea infinitely more, for he layes up his treaſure in heaven; where God hath bound himſelf to pay him with uſury and increaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AND now for the third thing,
<note n="3" place="margin">What it is to walk humbly.</note> 
                  <hi>What it is to walk humbly with God?</hi> it is not fit that I ſhould give you much more then the heads of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, unleſs I intended of a Sermon to make a treatiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore,
<note place="margin">To think meanly of our ſelves.</note> 
                  <hi>think lowly of thy ſelf,</hi> which is a great part of this duty. So the word <hi>humbly</hi> is often taken, eſpecially in compare with God, from whom we and all we have do come, and on whom they continually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. As thou giveſt to others <hi>their</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:106191:34"/>own, yea <hi>thine</hi> own; ſo aſſume to thy ſelf no more then is thine own: yea call nothing that is good thine own; but acknowledge God in all, be it riches, or beauty, or learning, or health, or grace it ſelf. When thou exerciſeſt <hi>juſtice and mercy,</hi> do not take it to be a matter of high deſert: but think that thou only doeſt as becomes a man, and thou doſt thy ſelf a great deal of right and kindneſs in it: and what thou doſt, it is from God, who gives both the will and ability to do it.</p>
               <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Bewail thy imperfections.</note> 
                  <hi>Mourn and lament over thy ſelf.</hi> Think lowly of thy ſelf, when thou art at the beſt: and then moan over, and bemoan thy ſelf, that thou art no better. This is called in <hi>Ahab,</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of himſelf, which though it were but outward, yet was anſwered with an outward bleſſing. And thus they are joyned together, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9, 10.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Obey Gods commands.</note> 
                  <hi>Readily ſubject thy ſelf to all Gods commands.</hi> He that truly mourns and is ſad that he is no better, ſtrives moſt ſincerely, and uſes all means to be as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106191:34"/>good as he can. His heart riſes not againſt any of Gods commands, he thinks nothing too ſtrict which God enjoyns. He willingly gives up his liberty and choice to God, which is an act of the greateſt humility imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Not my will (Lord) but thy will be done, is not only his language, but the ſenſe of his ſoul. And what greater ſubjection can there be in a man, then to have no will of his own, but to part with it unto another? This makes all ſin ſo abominable, becauſe it bids defiance to God, and diſowns in a proud ſort his authority: and this makes goodneſs ſo acceptable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it makes us lay our ſelves at Gods feet, to know his pleaſure, and debaſes us to nothing. We claim no power over our ſelves, or any thing that we have, own no right at all to diſpoſe of any thing as we pleaſe, when we humbly walk with God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And in particular,
<note place="margin">Worſhip him with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> we muſt <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently worſhip him</hi> by all Acts of prayer and praiſes. <hi>O come let us worſhip, and bow down, let us kneel before the Lord our maker,</hi> Pſal. 95.6. A Pſalm not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106191:35"/>appointed to be uſed heretofore in the beginning of divine ſervice, to remember us how reverently and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly we ſhould addreſs our ſelves unto Gods worſhip. And let me tell you this, that it becomes us to enter into the place where we tender out ſervices unto God, with more humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and compoſedneſs, then ordinarily now appears. It is not a ſign of a good Spirit, to come either with an haughty and high look, or with a careleſs and gariſh eye, much leſs laughing and talking, when we are going to humble our ſelves, and fall down before the Lord. But we ought to enter even into the place where we intend to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our obeyſance to him, with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thoughts, ſubmiſſive looks, and a baſhful countenance, as being deeply ſenſible of our unworthineſs to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach into his preſence. There is a tradition among the Hebrews, that <hi>David</hi> learnt but two things of <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> and he made him his maſter, his friend, and his privy-counſellour for them. And the one of them was by way of reproof, becauſe he came into
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106191:35"/>the School, the houſe of Teaching, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) with his head lifted up,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. P. Fagium in Pirk. Av. cap.</hi> 6.</note> which had the face of raſhneſs and pride in it. Oh that men would now profit ſo much by reproofs, and count them their friends that tell them of their faults; and that they would learn likewiſe to come into the houſe of God with more becoming reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in their faces then ordinarily they do!</p>
               <p n="5">5.
<note n="5" place="margin">Exerciſe meekneſs in afflictions.</note> 
                  <hi>Meekly ſubmit to Gods correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> As thou muſt not chuſe thy <hi>work,</hi> ſo neither muſt thou chuſe thy <hi>uſage.</hi> All impatience comes from pride, and our murmurings are bred by too goodly thoughts of our own ſelves. Alas! what are we, more then many others, that we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be ſo tenderly handled? What great matters can we do with that health, or riches, or credit, which we would never have to abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from us? Nay, what condition is bad enough for ſuch wretches? What a wonder is it, that ſuch unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable creatures are not baniſhed out of the world? If we thought thus
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106191:36"/>oft-times with our ſelves, we ſhould become very <hi>humble; i e.</hi> meek, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and contented under all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls us. One act of <hi>humility</hi> begets another; and he that thinks meanly of himſelf, will not be angry that he is afflicted.</p>
               <p n="6">6.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Subjection to our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors.</note> 
                  <hi>Be peaceable and obedient to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors,</hi> who are gods in the world, and to whom God hath bidden us, that we ſhould ſubject our ſelves. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupream, or unto Governors,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. It is an high act of pride and inſolency, to controle the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that is over us, and to ſet up our own wills above Gods vicegerents. For it is a great contempt of the maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God, whoſe <hi>image</hi> they more remarkably bear, and with whoſe <hi>effigies</hi> they are more viſibly ſtampt then other men. We muſt alway therefore do what they command us, or elſe ſuffer what they inflict upon us. And if we chuſe the latter, we muſt ſuffer as meekly and peaceably, as if it was an immediate hand of heaven
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106191:36"/>upon us. For if <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay of every man, <hi>That proud and haughty ſcorner is his name, who dealeth in proud wrath, Prov.</hi> 21.24. then much more is he to be branded in the for-head, for a man ſuperlatively proud, who cannot endure to be touched in body or eſtate, but it caſts him into the higheſt inflammations of anger, even againſt the <hi>higheſt powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
                  <note place="margin">Temperance and ſobriety in the uſe of what we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</note> 
                  <hi>Moderately and temperately uſe Gods mercies.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies to be temperate, is applyed frequently to the mind, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to pride and ſelf-conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For ſobriety indeed proceeds from an humble ſenſe, that nothing is ours, but all that we have is Gods; and that we have right to nothing, but what he gives, and as he allows. And all drunkenneſs, wantonneſs, and whatſoever other intemperance there is in the world, is commonly the iſſue of an haughty, giant-like temper of ſpirit, which makes men look upon themſelves as Lords and owners; and all creatures as their proper goods, which are perfectly at their diſpoſal.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106191:37"/>The <hi>crown of pride,</hi> and the <hi>drunkards of Ephraim,</hi> are both names for the ſame perſons, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.1, 3. For beſides that ſuch men have no regard to a ſupream being, they look bigg upon all their inferiours; and no beaſts likewiſe do kick more againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs or counſels of Gods Prophets, then ſuch as they.</p>
               <p n="8">8.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
                  <note place="margin">Modeſty in looking for a reward.</note> 
                  <hi>Modeſtly expect a reward from God,</hi> when thou haſt done theſe and all other good actions. That word which is here in my text rendred <hi>humble,</hi> doth frequently occurr in the Jewiſh writings, for <hi>ſhamefac'tneſs</hi> and <hi>modeſty.</hi> And therefore I add this at the laſt, as the top of all, that when we have done all our <hi>work</hi> with the greateſt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; yet we muſt look for our <hi>wages</hi> from meer mercy and benevolence. This <hi>humility</hi> is the greateſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the faireſt of all the graces in Gods ſight. We never look more beautiful, then when we bluſh at our own defects, and dare not caſt our eyes confidently upon God. The higheſt act of <hi>Faith,</hi> is a piece of the loweſt <hi>humility.</hi> When we rely moſt upon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106191:37"/>Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> we utterly diſclaim all our own <hi>merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as that act of <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby we caſt our ſelves on Gods mercy, is not all the acts of it, but ſuppoſes many others foregoing; even ſo it is in this act of <hi>humility,</hi> whereby we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelves unworthy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any reward from Gods hand: It is ſo far from being all the humility that God requires, that there muſt precede all the other acts which I have mentioned, before this can take its place. Many men can eaſily diſclaim all truſt in their own righteouſneſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have none to truſt in. But they are truly humble men, that are juſt and righteous, and yet truſt not in that for their acceptance with God to ſalvation. You cannot ſay, that a man is wiſe, becauſe he holds his peace, when he is dumb and tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed: But he is a wiſe perſon, who can ſpeak well, and yet ſilently hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens. No more can he be deemed poor in ſpirit, who hath no riches nor treaſures in his ſoul to brag of; but he only, who is enriched with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106191:38"/>and faith, and love, and all good works, and yet is lowly in heart, poor in his own thoughts, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that he is but an unprofitable ſervant.</p>
               <p>Now all this is but <hi>juſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The juſtice and goodneſs of all this.</note> becauſe of our dependance on God, his ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over us, and his excellency above us. On all which when we look, we muſt ſay with <hi>Job,</hi> 42.5, 6. <hi>Now mine eye ſeeth thee; and therefore I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes.</hi> And it is no leſs <hi>good,</hi> then it is juſt. For <hi>firſt, He that lyes low, lyes ſafe.</hi> He cannot fall far, who ſtands on the ground; but whether can he fall who lyes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready upon it? We ſhall not be in danger to tumble down from great hopes and expectations, if we be ſo humble as to have no high opinion of our ſelves and deſervings. The loweſt valleys are the ſafeſt from wind and ſtorms; and God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to preſerve the meek, and that they ſhall inherit the earth. Who will harm modeſt and ſubmiſſive perſons; that had rather put up an injury, then do any; that are loving, peaceable,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106191:38"/>and quiet in the Land? None but thoſe, againſt whom no men be defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And ſecondly, <hi>He that lyes low, is moſt fruitful.</hi> The mountains are commonly barren, and the valleys are moſt richly laden. For the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the proud, but he gives grace to the humble. And thirdly, <hi>He that lyes low, is bleſſed from above with all that is good for him.</hi> The leſs he expects, the more he ſhall have; the more unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy he judges himſelf to be, the more fit he is to have his emptineſs filled. The ſhowres that run of from the high heads of mountains, run down into the boſom of valleys. Moſt of heavens plenty falls into the loweſt places; and ſo do moſt of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and bleſſings fall into humble ſouls. They that behave themſelves as it becomes them, in meekneſs, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, obedience, modeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God will make good his Word unto them. The meek ſhall eat and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord; They ſhall lye down, and none ſhall make them afraid. He will keep them in perfect peace, in a ſweet ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106191:39"/>and quiet of Spirit. He will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt them in due time, and open even the gate of heaven unto them; not to pour down bleſſings on them, as now he doth; but to receive them up to his bleſſings. This diſcourſe would ſwell too much, if I ſhould particularly ſhow the goodneſs of every one of the fore-mentioned acts of humility; and therefore it ſhall ſuffice to have given theſe light touches upon ſome of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>NOW if theſe things be ſo as I have diſcourſed;
<note place="margin">Application.</note> then <hi>firſt</hi> let us begin to put in practice a part of the duty laſt mentioned,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">Be humbled for ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe commands.</note> by <hi>being deeply humbled</hi> for all our ſins, againſt theſe plain and familiar commands Let every man ſearch into himſelf how far he hath gone along with the ſtream; for it is manifeſt, that covetouſneſs and oppreſſion, hard heartedneſs and cruelty, pride and irreligion, have come in like a flood upon us in this Nation, and born many away before them. As for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> we may take up
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106191:39"/>the complaint of <hi>Petrarch</hi> concerning the Age wherein he lived, that hunters and fowlers uſe not greater cunning in laying their nets and ſnares for wild beaſts and fowls, then crafty men do to inveigle and inſnare the ſimple and plain-meaning people. Or we may ſay with one of his Countrey-men (which is now become a proverb in <hi>Italy</hi>) <hi>That by deceit and cunning, men live half the year, and by cunning and deceit the other half.</hi> And <hi>Mercy</hi> is ſuch a ſtranger to mens hearts, that we count him a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of great tenderneſs, that will not deceive us at all; and a very merciful creature, who will not deceive us as much as he can. So little kindneſs and good nature is ſtirring; that we are apt to ſuſpect them of deſigns, who make much of us; and we dare ſcarce receive mens courteſies. And what is a great deal of our <hi>Religion,</hi> but an humourſom kind of devotion; a proud ſelf conceited pleaſing of our ſelves, with a faſtidious contempt of all others? Where is that awefulneſs in mens countenances when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with God; that tenderneſs of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106191:40"/>heart at the mention of any of his commands; that bewailing of their ſins; that patience, peaceableneſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of the puniſhment of their iniquities that ought to appear? We may almoſt ſay with this Prophet in the next Chapter, <hi>The good man is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed out of the earth,
<note place="margin">Mic. 7.2.</note> and there is none upright among men.</hi> For could there be ſo much ſpoil (think you) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the midſt of us, and no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice? Such eſtates ſo quickly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and no covetouſneſs? So much blood ſhed, and no hatreds? So many contentions, quarrels and hot diſputes; and no uncharitableneſs? So many vain opinions, and no pride? Such un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteadineſs in the wayes of God, and no ſelf-conceitedneſs in mens hearts? Such contempt of the Miniſtry and all that is ſacred, and no irreligion? We muſt begin therefore to amend, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging theſe ſins, and ſeriouſly bemoaning them, either in our ſelves or others.</p>
               <p>But our amendment muſt not end here,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">Amend in all theſe things.</note> nor muſt we think by blubbered eyes and lamentable groans, to draw
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106191:40"/>God to be a party with us in theſe ſins. No, we muſt ſincerely proceed to a practice of all theſe duties, which the Prophet and our own conſciences loudly call for; and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have been ſo much laid aſide and neglected, or at leaſt, ſome of them ſet up to thruſt out all the reſt.</p>
               <p>And <hi>firſt</hi> for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> let us put away all iniquity, if there be any in our hands, and all covetous deſires which we find lurking in our hearts.
<note place="margin">Firſt be more juſt.</note> Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſay as the Pſalmiſt doth, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.23, 24. <hi>Search me O God, and know my heart, try me, and know my thoughts: And ſee if there be any wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked way in me, and lead me in the way everlaſting.</hi> If thou haſt wronged any man, make him ſatisfaction. Owe nothing to any man, but to love one another. Detain not the wages of the hireling. Let no man go beyond his Brother, or defraud him in any thing. Let his relations, and goods, and every thing he hath, be as an <hi>holy thing</hi> to thee, which thou mayſt not lay thine hand upon. We are told of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106191:41"/>an heathen people who were ſo juſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aelian. var. hiſt. l.</hi> 4. 1.</note> that if they found any thing in the high-way, they would not take it up, thinking the owner would come ere long to ſeek it, to whom it did of right belong. I wiſh there were but half ſo much juſtice among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who not only cozen others when it comes in their way, and have fair opportunities preſented, but uſe all ſorts of circumventions, and will go a great way about to ſeek an occaſion to deceive them. It is grown to be an art and a ſtudy how to cheat a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and whereas thoſe heathen boggled at an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as they called it) a thing which was <hi>found,</hi> and thought it an injury to take it up; Chriſtians make no ſcruple of a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as I may phraſe it) an injuſtice which they <hi>ſeek</hi> for, and are inquiſitive to find wayes of bringing it to paſs. And ſad it is to conſider, for how little men will venture to diſpleaſe God, and what a ſmall gain will tempt them to do unjuſtly. If a man could get all the world by one act of unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he would be a great loſer by the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106191:41"/>bargain; but there are ſuch vile and cheap ſouls, that will not ſtick for a ſmall ſum of money, perhaps for no ſum at all to do not one, but many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious acts to their neighbours. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſideration (methinks) would amend men in ſuch a matter as this; and the thoughts only of its folly might work a cure upon them without a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon againſt it. Fear of loſing <hi>all</hi> might make them carefull not to have <hi>a farthing</hi> that is got unjuſtly, if they had but ſo much obſervation as little children, who uſe to ſay, that after they once cheat, they never thrive in their games. I know it is a deſire of being rich, and indeed of being rich preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that thruſts men forward into ſuch baſe and unworthy courſes; But God doth ſo order it, that nothing more hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the accompliſhment of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire, then the way they take to attain it. There is a great truth in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> proverb, that <hi>He who will be rich in one year, ſhall be hang'd at the half years end.</hi> Exceeding greedineſs may make men do ſuch villanous acts that they cannot be indured, but are brought to ruine
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106191:42"/>by them. But howſoever in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of the wiſe man, there is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible verity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.22. <hi>He that haſteth to be rich, hath an evil eye; and conſidereth not that poverty ſhall come upon him.</hi> See alſo <hi>v.</hi> 20. and <hi>chap.</hi> 20.22. Put away therefore all falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and guile; all covetouſneſs and violence; if it be but to ſave the eſtate that you have, and that you may get more, and have it laſt longer: But you will conſult better for your ſelves if you do thus out of obedience to God, and reſpect to your Brethren; as it is a part of that duty which God and man oblige you unto.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> they are engaged above all other men to do juſtly, ſeeing they are the <hi>leaders</hi> of the people, by whoſe examples they are inclined to live,
<note place="margin">V. Cardinal. de Oſſat. Epiſt. 66. part. 1. &amp; Epiſt. 81. <hi>Les Roys &amp; autres primes Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns ſe perm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ettoient toutes choſes qui tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noient à leur profit,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and by whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous management of things they live happily. It was a moſt pernicious Maxime, and altogether unworthy of a good man (as one of his own party in expreſs terms acknowledges) which Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eighth had often in his mouth, viz. <hi>That Kings and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106191:42"/>Princes may do any thing which will make for their profit.</hi> And a ſhame it is to their religion that he could add in juſtification of this ſaying, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are come to ſuch a paſs, that it is not at all imputed to them, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to their diſhonour, if they break their faith, forſwear themſelves, lie, betray their allies, and do any other thing of like nature. But theſe wicked principles which he made uſe of on purpoſe to perſwade the King of <hi>France</hi> to break his league with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> are moſt excellently confronted by a golden ſpeech of that Cardinal who reports theſe things,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>77. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>au Monſ. de Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy.</hi>
                  </note> in which all ſuch perſons are much concerned. <hi>At the foot of the account</hi> ſaith he (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of King <hi>James</hi> his moderation when he came to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) <hi>You ſhall find, that the better and more juſtly any man ſhall rule, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory of God, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, profit and happineſs of his ſubjects; the more aſſured his eſtate ſhall be; the more ſtrong, the more beloved and bleſſed ſhall he be of God, and men: in which conſiſts the true and laſting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106191:43"/>grandeur and puiſſance of Kings, and the aſſurance of their poſterity.</hi> Nay <hi>Age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilaus</hi> had better notions of Divine things in this particular then that <hi>Pope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch. in Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Ageſ. &amp; in Apotheg.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> who when ſome told him the <hi>Great King</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the King of <hi>Perſia</hi>) would have it ſo; anſwered, <hi>How can he be greater then me, unleſs he be more juſt and more ſober?</hi> Upon the mentioning of which, <hi>Plutarch</hi> gives this excellent admonition, <hi>By juſtice, as by a royal ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, we ſhould take the meaſure of mens heights one above another.</hi> If we were in a ſtate of war, and one ſhould make a motion to ſuch great perſons <hi>to do juſtly,</hi> perhaps he might receive ſuch an anſwer as <hi>Antigonus</hi> gave a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher who preſented him with a treatiſe of this ſubject; <hi>Thou art a fool to give me now a book concerning juſtice, when thou ſeeſt I am beſieging other mens Castles, and making war upon their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> But when things are ſetled, and when it is apparent that violent dealing comes upon mens own heads; then ſure a man may be believed, if he ſay, that there is no other way to thrive, nor can a <hi>Prince</hi> live by any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106191:43"/>doctrine as that of Juſtice and piety. Then ſure, if not at other times, one may propoſe the example of an heathen Emperour to them,
<note place="margin">Alex. Severus. Quod tibi fieri non vis, alteri ne feceris. Al. Lamprid.</note> who was ſo taken with that ſaying of our Saviours, <hi>Math.</hi> 7.12. that he cauſed this ſentence to be writ in ſundry places upon the walls of his pallace, <hi>Do not that to another, which thou wouldſt not have done to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all under-officers and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of publique buiſineſs had need hear this doctrine continually ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ears, becauſe it is ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their worldly intereſts to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it exactly. When men have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and opportunity to gratifie their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous deſires, they will find that they need a very divine power to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them to deny them.
<note place="margin">Balzack.</note> 
                  <q>It is very ſtrange (ſaith the Maſter of modern Eloquence) that the great <hi>Turk</hi> can intruſt his wives to the vigilancy of others, and aſſure himſelf their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity will thereby be conſerved; yet that <hi>Kings</hi> know not to whom they may ſafely encharge their treaſures. But the true reaſon is, for that an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man is by ſo much more difficultly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106191:44"/>found then an <hi>Eunuch,</hi> by how much <hi>miracles</hi> are more rare then <hi>Monſters.</hi> Great fortitude is requiſite to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of honeſty, but the will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffices to become covetous.</q> And therefore ſeeing it is neceſſary to do ſome violence to our ſelves, to keep us from doing violence to others; ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have great reaſon to thank thoſe who will lay their hands daily upon their corrupt affections by holy admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions &amp; counſels; not only to reſtrain &amp; ſetter, but to ſlay and mortifie them.</p>
               <p>And to conclude this; let us all be ſure to remember it is not enough to praiſe juſtice, and make ſpeeches in its commendation; nor to have ſome affection to it by convictions in our minds of its reaſonableneſs and profit; but we muſt <hi>do juſtly,</hi> as my text ſpeaks: and all our actions muſt be conform to the principles which we praiſe. This I ſay the rather, becauſe it hath been noted that men of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>intellectuals</hi> have had bad <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls:</hi> and thoſe who have writ books for the preſervation of honeſty, have not preſerved themſelves from corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:106191:44"/>
               <p>Now Secondly, for <hi>Mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let mercy be joyned with juſtice.</note> it makes a more ſpecial claim to our favour, becauſe we ſtand ſo much in need of it every day, if not from other men, yet from God. And it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that the Prophet, though juſtice is to be loved, yet doth not ſay <hi>Love juſtice,</hi> but <hi>Love mercy;</hi> becauſe he would recommend it to our deareſt affections. For there are more <hi>juſt men,</hi> then there are <hi>mercifull</hi> in the world; it being eaſier to give men their <hi>own,</hi> then to beſtow upon them what is <hi>ours.</hi> Oh, to part with this earth, this Idol of Gold and Silver, is a hard leſſon: to give to him that asks, to do good to him that doth evil to us, is an harſh ſaying. But remember what <hi>Zacheus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Not only I reſtore four fold to him whom I have wronged; but half of my goods I give to the poor.</hi> Of ſuch a charitable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition muſt you be, if you hope to go to heaven, and care no more for riches then do your little children. You muſt not make hard bargains with poor men, nor think every penny overplus too much for them. You muſt uſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106191:45"/>ſometimes to give more then you have agreed for; that ſo you may be ready and diſpoſed to do an act of charity when the poor call for it. I know it hath been frequently pleaded, that the times are hard and dangerous, and that mens eſtates are much impoveriſhed. But then (1) they are harder you may be ſure with the poor, if they be hard with you who are rich. If they make you cry, they make them groan. If they pinch your purſe, then they ſqueeze and drain their very houſes. And (2) mercifulneſs is the way to make them better. When they have made us better and become more charitable, then they themſelves will grow better, &amp; become more peaceable. <hi>He that hath a bountifull eye ſhall be bleſſed. He that hath mercy upon the poor, happy is he,</hi> Prov. 14.21. Prov. 22.9. And (3) the worſe and more dangerous they are, the leſs we ſhould be in love with riches, and the more we ſhould give away to them that need. For it is likely we cannot keep them or by giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome away we may ſecure the reſt. As men that are afraid their goods will
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106191:45"/>be loſt by ſtorms at Sea, give ſo much in the hundred to aſſure them; ſo ſhould we aſſure our goods and eſtates with God when the times are tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous, by giving him a large ſumm for his uſes. A wiſer man then any of us makes the badneſs of the times an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument unto charity, howſoever now it is a motive to many to ſhut their hands. <hi>Give a portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, for thou knoweſt not what evill ſhall be upon the earth.</hi> Eccleſ. 11.2. His meaning is, the time may come when thy treaſure ſhall be taken from thee, and how much better is it to part with them voluntarily? Thou canſt not tell how much danger all thou haſt will be in: and therefore it is wiſdom to intruſt God with it, and give him ſomething in hand, that he may ſave the reſt. And (4.) if God do not ſave thy riches, yet he may wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſave thee. For he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1, 2.3.) to preſerve the merciful men in time of trouble and ſickneſs. Or (5) if he take ſuch men away, it is when he intends to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a place, and then who would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106191:46"/>to live? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1 If they be taken away from the evil to come, then death doth them a great deal of good, and God is very merciful to ſuch merciful men, in not letting them ſee the deſolation of their countrey. To all which add, that while we live, <hi>we have no more then we do enjoy, and then we give away for Gods ſake.</hi> And there is no leſs of mercy in <hi>forgiving</hi> of men, then in <hi>giving</hi> to them, in paſſing by the evil they do to us, then in doing good to them; but leſt this diſcourſe ſhould proceed to over great a length, I muſt leave you to judge how much we ſhould <hi>love</hi> it by what hath been ſaid of this.</p>
               <p>And then thirdly for <hi>walking hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> with God,
<note place="margin">And thirdly, humble walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God be joyned with them both.</note> let me only ſuggeſt theſe two things from the word <hi>walk,</hi> which I have not yet taken notice of. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it ſignifies more then one ſingle act, and engages us to a continued mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the wayes of humility. Our demeanour towards God muſt be a <hi>life</hi> of lowlineſs, meekneſs and patience; a <hi>courſe</hi> of contentedneſs and ſobriety, modeſty and moderation; a conſtant
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106191:46"/>
                  <hi>ſeries</hi> of ſuch actions as I have named. And if we think to come to heaven by taking a ſtep or two in this way, or by fierce running at ſometimes, we ſhall be but like to a traveller who fits ſtill the moſt of his day, and thinks to come to his journeys end by ſome ſudden ſpurts toward night. To main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a conſtant ſenſe of our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on God; a continual converſe with him: &amp; to have a perpetual care in all things to pleaſe him, by conforming our wills to him; are things ſo neceſſary, that we are but <hi>nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Chriſtians without them. And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> to <hi>walk</hi> humbly ſignifies more then an inward perſwaſion, and denotes ſomething outward that is to be ſeen by the world. God will not accept of that which people call a good heart, a pious reſolution and right meaning; but he will have us <hi>walk</hi> before all men in the way of his commandments, and publiquely appear in oppoſition to the wickedneſs that is in the world. If we think one thing and do another, the greater is the ſin, &amp; the greater will be the condemnation, becauſe we know ſo well and do ſo ill.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:106191:47"/>
               <p>Not to mention any thing beſides that may be included in the phraſe; I beſeech you put theſe things in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.
<note place="margin">Theſe things muſt be done, and not only praiſed.</note> I have perſwaded you enough, do but perſwade your ſelves. All men commend juſtice, yet they do unjuſtly. Vertue hath every ones good word, though they live ungodlily. The proud man commends humility; and the covetous man praiſes Charity; and the unrighteous man ſpeaks for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. Men complement with godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and they court vertue, but none will have her. She is poor, and will not conſent to their baſe deſires; and ſo though they extoll her beauty, they will none of her. So in <hi>Italy</hi> they have a proverb among the husbandmen, <hi>laudandos eſſe montes, ſed à planitie non recedendum. Commend the mountains, but live in the vallies.</hi> It is fine ſweet air that breaths on the top of hills and affords a pleaſant wholſome dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; but keep there where moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit dwells, and that is in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. It is ſad that men ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch a proverb as far as heaven, and commend the holy hill of God,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106191:47"/>and all the graces and pleaſures that ſtand on the top of it; but reſolve ſtill to dwell below, and love the things that are beneath, better then all thoſe that are above. Yea though it be a meer dunghill, they will embrace it, if it be but fat, and will yield them plenty of worldly increaſe. They like goodneſs when they conſider it alone; but when they conſider it with other things, they take their eaſe and profit to be much better. So <hi>Soph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cles</hi> ſaid in that advice which too many follow,
<q>
                     <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Praiſe righteouſneſs, but ſtick faſt to thy gain.</hi> Let it have thy good word, but do as thou ſeeſt good for thy ſelf. But I beſeech him that readeth theſe things, that by what hath been ſaid, he would riſe above approbations and commendations of godlineſs, and heartily ſubject himſelf unto the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it: or if he love a ſofter word, let him embrace it, and marry himſelf to it; let the match now be made up, if he be yet but a complementer in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106191:48"/>Religion, and not really wedded to it.</p>
               <p>I will only add,
<note place="margin">They muſt not be divided from each other.</note> that all thoſe three are ſo linked and chain'd together, that they are inſeparable, and we cannot take one but we muſt have all. He cannot <hi>walk humbly</hi> with God who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves not all the rules of <hi>juſtice</hi> and common honeſty, with <hi>mercy</hi> alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men. God will give him no thanks that goes againſt his conſcience and known Laws to do him ſervice, (as they are pleaſed to ſtile it.) No, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Plato in Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone.</note> &amp;c. Let neither thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) or thy life, nor any thing elſe be deerer to thee then juſtice, that thou mayſt have wherewith to anſwer for thy ſelf when thou comeſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> into the other world. Elſe we (ſay the Laws which he there intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces ſpeaking their part) ſhall be thy enemies, and more then we, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>our Brethren</hi> will be againſt thee: the Laws in that world will not courteouſly receive and treat thee.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And then on the other ſide, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>juſt</hi> and mercifull to men, unleſs we walk <hi>humbly</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> Juſtice it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106191:48"/>ſelf ſhould ſpring from a ſenſe that we are under a divine Law, and are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the heavenly Soveraign. And true godlineſs is but a piece of juſtice toward God, as honeſt dealing in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the world is juſtice toward men. We do a manifeſt wrong to God, and deal diſhoneſtly with him, if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from him ſolemn and conſtant worſhip of him. We are baſe cheaters &amp; defrauders, when we let our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs, though never ſo juſtly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, rob God of our beſt thoughts and affections. And what high-way robbers then and notorious felons are thoſe who ſuffer their ſports and pleaſures, if not their more beaſtly luſts to do violence to all religious duties? Many of this ſort are ſo highly inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to God, that they not only ſteal all they can from godlineſs and piety, but they wound and ſtab it with the ſword of their tongues; and if they were able, would ſtrike it dead, as they oft-times leave it gaſping for life. And this they do with an high hand and great inſolency; as if thoſe who moſt humbly ſubmit themſelves to all
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106191:49"/>Chriſts commands, and are moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of doing any wrong to God, were to be eſteemed our greateſt enemies, and thoſe that ſhould ſuffer all wrong from men. That Noble Philoſopher I juſt now mentioned, hath a leſſon for them as well as for the former, if they will be ſo juſt either to God or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as to learn it: <hi>In my opinion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>piety and holineſs about the ſervice and worſhip of God is one part of juſtice; and the other part of it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the ſerving of men.</hi> Let no man therefore pride himſelf in this, that he is not lyable to the charge of any creature, when God hath ſo much to ſay againſt him for neglect of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato in Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prone,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> reading his word, praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him for every good thing he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, if not mocking at all theſe. And let this be eſteemed true excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (which we ſhould have the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to maintain in the worſt of times) <hi>not to bluſh at Chriſtian vertues, nor to boaſt of moral ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And when we have done what we can upon our ſelves and thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us, then let us pray for others;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106191:49"/>eſpecially thoſe that rule us,
<note place="margin">Let us pray for others, and principally for our Rulers, that they may do theſe things.</note> that we may have juſt, mercifull and religious Governours. Our prayers will be the more acceptable for them, when we pray but for that which we do our ſelves in our own places; and their juſtice and goodneſs will be the more ſweet to us, when it is the fruit of our earneſt prayers. Let us beſeech there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Lord and Governour of the world who rules the Nations in righteouſneſs and truth, that all thoſe who do or ſhall bear any part in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of theſe Lands, may be ſuch as will take away no mans rights, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our Laws, pitty the poor, and not exact great fums meerly to ſupport their own greatneſs. Let us pray that thoſe may rule us who are ruled by their maker, that will do good even to enemies, walk humbly with their God, be poor in ſpirit, not given to the vanities and exceſſes of the world; that will ſympathize with a poor Nation in its poverty, pitty it miſeries; not prodigally waſt its trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: and ſuch as will love Religion, and make the worſhip of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106191:50"/>and the practice of all Chriſtian duties had in high eſteem.</p>
               <p>Such Rulers the Lord will love and bleſs:
<note place="margin">See alſo <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 15, 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.14. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.14, 15.</note> and both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>people</hi> will feel the bleſſing that is in them. For ſo the wiſeſt King that ever was tells us, Prov. 25.5. <hi>That if the wicked be taken from before the King, his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs.</hi> And if it be ſo eſtabliſhed, then <hi>the King by judgement eſtabliſheth the Land,</hi> Prov. 29.4. <hi>All the people rejoyce when the righteous are in authority; and by a man of underſtanding and knowledge the ſtate of a land is prolonged,</hi> Prov. 29.2. 28.2. That which the Biſhop of <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas</hi> ſaid to the eſtates of <hi>Portugal</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had reſtored that family to the Crown which had long been excluded by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> is the greateſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of a <hi>Prince</hi> to the peoples affection, next to true piety; <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>doth not eſteem thoſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes lawfull which were paid in tears; and he will not reign over your goods, nor over your heads, nor over your privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, but over your hearts.</hi> He that by ſuch a government as this doth ſeat
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106191:50"/>himſelf in the affection of God and his people: <hi>his throne ſhall be eſt abliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever, and his children are bleſſed after him,</hi> Prov. 29.14.20.7, 8. I will conclude this with the words of the ſame wiſe <hi>King,</hi> which concern every man of us: <hi>He that followeth after righteouſneſs and mercy, findeth life, righteouſneſs and honour,</hi> ch 21.21. <hi>By humility and the fear of the Lord, are riches, and honour, and life,</hi> Pro. 22.4.</p>
               <p>And when God hath heard theſe prayers, may we be ſo wiſe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to chuſe ſuch <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in future times, as conſiſt of perſons <hi>juſt</hi> and righteous, <hi>mercifull</hi> and tender of all mens intereſts and concernments; and that <hi>walk with God,</hi> not living in any ſin; and that <hi>walk humbly</hi> with him, not being puft up with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of their own godlineſs: That are neither ungodly themſelves, nor call all others ungodly who are not of their mind; That love not thoſe who are bad; nor ſcorn any that are good; And in brief, that are not ſwoln with a belief of their own excellencies, nor grown heady and proud in opinions;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106191:51"/>but men of a ſober Religion toward God, joyned with juſtice and charity toward man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Shall not exerciſe the Readers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience any longer about theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<note place="margin">The <hi>ſixth</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</note> when I have but briefly opened the <hi>ſixth</hi> obſervation which naturally arriſes from the diſcourſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, viz. <hi>That theſe things</hi> [to do juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to love mercy, to walk humbly with God] <hi>were alwayes more valued by God then Sacrifices, or any other bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (though coſtly) ſervices.</hi> It is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intent of the man of God in this place to diſparage all outward worſhip though of Gods own appointment (and much more all their own deviſed ſervices) if it were not joyned with true purity of heart and piety of life. For there is nothing reaches the ſoul but theſe things that I have been treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of; nothing but theſe conform us unto <hi>God,</hi> who is a pure ſpirit: nothing is everlaſting and of an immortal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but this image of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this he would work in us that we
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106191:51"/>may be bleſſed. But I need not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this manner to give you the <hi>reaſon</hi> of it, you will preſently conclude the truth of the obſervation if I do but ſhew you <hi>firſt</hi> that theſe are the things which God always required above all the other:
<note place="margin">Two things to be proved.</note> and <hi>ſecondly</hi> that all the other things did tend to the advancement of theſe. You may well expect I ſhould take this method, for your own ſouls will bid you enquire, why God did appoint ſacrifices, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, abundance of waſhings, and other ceremonies, if he was not mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed with them.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>firſt</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate that God was not pleaſed with ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and things of that nature,
<note n="1" place="margin">Sacrifices not ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from juſtice, mercy and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: but that rather they were an abomination to him and like the ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carkaſs without the ſoul, when ſo ſeparated.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Look into the times before the <hi>law,</hi> &amp; you ſhall ſee that there is no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy commended for offering ſacrifices, or for loving any of theſe outward ſhadows, but only for theſe ſubſtantial
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106191:52"/>vertues which my Text ſpeaks of. It is ſaid of <hi>Enoch, that he walked with God. and that God took him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Proved from the times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law.</note> Gen. 5.22, 24. but it is not ſaid that he was very libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in ſlaying of beaſts, and that he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to heaven in the ſmoak of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices. And it is ſaid of <hi>Noah, that he was a juſt man and perfect in his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and one that walked with God.</hi> Gen. 6.9. but nothing is there ſaid where he is commended of building Altars, and making great ſtore of oblations to God. Though they did theſe things, and it is recorded of them that they did them: yet their character is not fetcht from ſuch things, nor do you read that God commends them upon their account. And ſo of <hi>Abraham,</hi> it is ſaid that he left his own countrey and believed God: and this ſaith the Apoſtle, was accounted to him for righteouſneſs. His high thoughts of God, his ſubmiſſion to him, his depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on him, his forſaking all for him, his truſting of life and every thing he had in his hands: his obeying God and following of him whitherſovever he would lead him: and in ſhort his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106191:52"/>reſignation of himſelf, child, and all things elſe to Gods will. Theſe were the acts for which God account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him his friend. But we do not read that God or the Apoſtle commend him for being circumciſed: no, <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was but the ſeal of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of that faith which he had in uncircumciſion,</hi> Rom. 4.11. <hi>i. e.</hi> It did but teſtifie to him that his faith was good and ſound, becauſe God hereby took him into a covenant with himſelf: or, it was that mark and outward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken whereby God did aſſure him of his acceptance into a covenant of great bleſſings for himſelf and ſeed, becauſe he had believed on him, and was righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And not to proceed any further to others that ſucceeded preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him,
<note place="margin">And from the times when the Law was given.</note> but to look to the time of the Law: You may obſerve that the <hi>ten commandments</hi> were given by God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gave any of the other Laws, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. And likewiſe you may take notice of the ordinary ſtyle of <hi>Moſes</hi> when he ſpeaks of theſe things, which runs thus; Theſe are the <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106191:53"/>the Statutes and the judgements,</hi> Deut. 6.1. or <hi>keep his Commandments, his Statutes and judgements,</hi> Deut. 30.14. the like to which you may read, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.4. In all which places, and many other, <hi>Commandments</hi> are put firſt, which word comprehends the moral and everlaſting precepts: and then follows <hi>Statutes,</hi> which denotes the Ordinances and inſtitutions about Gods Worſhip; and after that <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which ſignifies the Laws about matters of civil right, both which were alterable and not eternal. Yea the whole book of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> (or the <hi>ſecond Law</hi> as the word ſignifies) ſeems to be added after the other, to teach them that it was obedience to his voice in all things that God did moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. And therefore <hi>Nazianzen</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning up the priviledges of the Jews, ſaith that they had <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a double giving of the Law, <hi>Orat.</hi> 13. one <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Letter, the other <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Spirit. Which may be interpreted of that in mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and of the other in the plains of <hi>Jordan.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:106191:53"/>
               <p n="3">3. And ſo after the Law was given,
<note place="margin">And from the ſucceeding Ages.</note> all the people of God underſtood that the things chiefly intended by him, were their inward mortification, their purity and integrity of ſoul: a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual worſhip, and a life of temperance, ſobriety, juſtice, mercy, humility and all other vertues. To this there are a multitude of places in holy Writ that will teſtifie and bear witneſs. <hi>Hath the Lord as great pleaſure</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Samuel) <hi>in burnt offerings and ſacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? Behold, to obey is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken then the fat of ramms. For rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubborneſs is as iniquity and idolatry,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.22, 23.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Samuel</hi> a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> thought that God was delighted, if they feaſted him with a multitude of ſacrifices, and that nothing diſtaſted him if they had a care not to entertain <hi>Idols</hi> with the good chear at the Altar: and therefore <hi>Samuel</hi> tells him that God took the greateſt pleaſure in an hearty obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his commands, which was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all the outward worſhip that he had appointed; and that rebellion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106191:54"/>againſt Gods commands, was as bad as Idolatry and worſhipping of ſtocks and ſtones. From the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> let us go to <hi>Aſaph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And <hi>Aſaph.</hi>
                  </note> who lived not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and he tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.7, 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that God did not hunger after the fleſh of beaſts and foul, nor thirſt after the blood of Bulls and Goats: nor did he fall out with them for the neglect of this kind of ſervice; but that which he required of them was to pray to him, and praiſe him, and perform all their vows promiſes to him, which was the beſt of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15. And that which he reproves and chides them for, was that they hated inſtruction, and made nothing of all his commands for the regulating of their words, deſires and actions, <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17, 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He asks them how they dare be ſo impudent as to pretend be in covenant with him (though they brought him never ſo many fat ſacrifices) ſeeing they could not indure any of his counſels, but were unjuſt, unclean, lyers, ſwearers, ſlanderers and backbiters. As long as their evil affections and deſires were
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106191:54"/>
                  <hi>unmortified,</hi> he cared not for the <hi>death</hi> of ſo many of his creatures. And ſo you may read the ſenſe of <hi>David</hi> in the next Pſalm, Pſal. 51.15, 16, 17.
<note place="margin">And <hi>David.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O Lord open my lips, and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe. For thou deſireſt not ſacrifice, elſe would I give it: thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt not in burnt-offerings. The Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of God, are a broken ſpirit; a broken and a contrite heart O God thou wilt not deſpiſe.</hi> There were no Sacrifices in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed appointed for murder and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery (to which he hath a particular reſpect) but they made a man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to death by <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law; Yet he ſaith in General, that God did not <hi>delight in burnt-offerings,</hi> and ſo his words may be extended farther than that one caſe of his. That which pleaſed God was holy praiſes, and the ſacrifices of a broken heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirit. There may be an alluſion to the ceremonial worſhip in the words <hi>broken</hi> &amp; <hi>contrite;</hi> the former of which may refer to the ſacrifice of beaſts, the latter to the perfume that was put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the teſtimony of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, <hi>Exo.</hi> 30.35, 36. And
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106191:55"/>the words may ſignifie as if he had ſaid, that brokenneſs of heart, and an holy ſhivering of the ſpirit in pieces, ſo that it ſhall never be ſet together in the ſame frame wherein it was before, is far better then the cutting and chopping of the fleſh of beaſts in pieces. And as ſpices when they are beaten, ſmell the ſweeteſt; ſo when your hearts are thus bruiſed and laid in their own duſt by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere contrition, it is a more grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perfume to me then the <hi>beaten ſpices</hi> which were called moſt holy. If you look likewiſe into <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.30, 31. You ſhall find that to <hi>praiſe God with a ſong, and magnifie him with thanksgiving, pleaſe the Lord better then an Ox, or Bullock that hath horns and hoofs.</hi> From him paſs to <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſon, who is of the ſame judgement; for he ſaith expreſly, <hi>That to do juſtice and judgement is more acceptable to the Lord then Sacrifice.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And <hi>Solomon.</hi>
                  </note> Prov. 21.3. <hi>Yea that the ſacrifice of the wicked is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord, eſpecially when he bringeth it with a wicked mind,</hi> v. 27. And therefore in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. he bids
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106191:55"/>us <hi>be more ready to hear</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> to obey) <hi>then to offer the ſacrifices of fools.</hi> A fool is one that hath a body without a ſoul: and ſuch a carkaſs of religion are all ſacrifices without obedience: A meer skin and husk of devotion, which God can no more be pleaſed with, then we are with the gifts of a fool, who knows not what he doth. If from thence you paſs to the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And all the Prophets.</note> he ſpeaks ſo fully to my purpoſe in the firſt chapter from the eleventh verſe to the twenty-firſt that I need not gloſs upon his words. And <hi>chap.</hi> 63.1, 2, 3. the Lord tells that people who boaſted ſo much that they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided him with an houſe, and furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his table continually with ſacrifices, I need no houſe, nor am I beholden to you for a dwelling; for the heavens and the earth are mine. And I tell you there is no man loves me like to him that is poor in Spirit, humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to my word. Though you think that you pleaſe me mightily by the large proviſion you make at my houſe: believe it, without this contrition, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and holy trembling at my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106191:56"/>he that kills a whole Ox is ſo far from doing me any ſervice, that it is as bad as an act of murder: (becauſe he is an hypocrite and a baſe flatterer) And you may as well bring a dog or a pig to me (which was forbidden by the Law to be offered) as a lamb: Swines blood (which was the moſt deteſtable creature among them) is as good meat to me as the very beſt of your oblations: And you may as well fall down before an Idol and bleſs, as offer to me any incenſe. For indeed they made God but a great Idol, that could not ſee, nor hear their words and actions, much leſs their hearts and thoughts; and that would be pleaſed with any thing, and let them uſe him as they liſt. In the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> alſo the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that they had not hearkned to his words, nor to his law, but rejected it, 6.19. and leſt they ſhould return to this exprobration, that they had been very obedient in offering of ſacrifices, he faith, v. 20. <hi>To what purpoſe cometh there to me incenſe from</hi> Sheba, <hi>and the ſweet cane from a far country? your
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106191:56"/>burnt offerings are not acceptable, nor your ſacrifices ſweet unto me:</hi> Which is as if he ſhould have ſaid; Though you are at great coſt and charges about this outward worſhip, yet theſe are not the things that I ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: though you fetch me perfumes from forreign places, yet there are things nearer hand that are far more ſweet unto me. And he deals more plainly with them, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.21, 22, 23. &amp;c. ſaying, <hi>put your burnt offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to your ſacrifices, and eat fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>burnt offerings</hi> you know were to be wholly conſumed in the fire, and the people were to have none of them; but of their <hi>peace-offerings</hi> or ſacrifices of praiſe they did eat: Now ſaith God, Take all if you will for me; I care not for your burnt offerings: you may eat them your ſelves as you do the reſt, ſeeing you ſo little regard my other commands. Never think to flatter me with theſe, for I can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent if you feaſt upon them your ſelves. I am not ſo greedy of yourf ar ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as you imagine: no, it was not about them that I ſpake with your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106191:57"/>when they came out of <hi>Aegypt:</hi> but this was the thing that I command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, that they ſhould obey my voice in all things. But did not they ask leave of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (may ſome ſay) to go and offer Sacrifices in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? and did not God give them a Law about them? Yes, He did ſpeak to them indeed about thoſe things, but they were to be done in conjunction with better obedience: and compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively with the other things, he did not command them. It was never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that theſe ſhould be their righteouſneſs, and the things that they ſhould above all others perform: but <hi>obedience</hi> was the chief thing even in theſe that God reſpected. For ſo the words of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> may be underſtood, I did not command your fathers meerly concerning burn-offerings and ſacrifices, but the thing I aimed at, even in the appointing of them, was that they ſhould be obedient to my voice. To all this you may add that famous place cited by our Saviour <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.6. <hi>I deſired mercy and not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and the knowledge of God, more
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106191:57"/>then burnt offerings.</hi> I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks any thing of this matter: which might be perhaps, becauſe he wrote in the land of their Captivity, where ſacrifices were not offered. But leſt thoſe of the captivity ſhould think as their fore-fathers had done, that their ſacrifices were the things that he moſt delighted in: and that therefore he brought them from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> that they might offer them to him: He tells them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.23, 24. that they had not brought him any Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, nor honoured him with any offerings ſince they came to Babylon, and yet he would deliver them, which was a ſign that thoſe were not the things which he ſtood ſo much upon. No, inſtead of loading and wearying him with their Sacrifices (as their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors had done) they had rather made him ſerve with their ſins, and wearied him with their iniquities; So that it was only for his own names ſake that he blotted out their tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and did not remember their ſins, <hi>v.</hi> 25. And to conclude, an honeſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106191:58"/>Scribe in our Saviours time acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges the truth of all that I have ſaid, when he makes this reply to one of our Lords anſwers, <hi>There is one God, and there is none other but he. And to love him with all the heart &amp; with all the unaerſtanding, &amp; with all the ſoul &amp; with all the ſtrength, and to love his neighbour as himſelf; is more then all whole burnt offerings and ſacrifices,</hi> Mark. 12, 32, 33. Where we have a full confirmation of the words in my text and of that alſo which was ſaid a little before, that theſe duties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ten commandments, are the <hi>firſt and chiefeſt</hi> of all. For the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of this Scribe is, <hi>which is the firſt commandment of all?</hi> and our Saviour doth not ſay, to offer Sacrifices, which is neither <hi>firſt</hi> nor <hi>ſecond</hi> neither: But to love God he ſaith, is the prime and chiefeſt of all, and next to that is the love of our neighbour.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Hierod. &amp; Porphyr.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Plato Alcibiad.</hi> 2. <hi>Euſeb.</hi> .3. <hi>praep. Evang. C.</hi> 3.</note> I might add the ſenſe of ſober heathens, who thought that no ſacrifice would pleaſe God, but the oblation of a devout ſoul to him; and who looked upon theſe burnt offerings but as a needleſs butchery, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the food of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106191:58"/>fire, and nouriſhment of the flame: but then I ſhould too much exceed the juſt bounds of this diſcourſe, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo that there remains ſomething due to that great enquiry, which is, For what end were they and ſuch like things appointed by God, if they were not very pleaſing to him?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="2">2. THE truth is,
<note place="margin">Sacrifices tended to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more toward holineſs.</note> thoſe heathens did commonly ſtretch this notion ſo far, as to condemn all ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Euſeb. L.</hi> 4. <hi>Praepar. Svang. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.</note> ſome of them out of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their true uſe, and others out of falſe principles which they had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed; and therefore (waving other ends, and keeping only to the purpoſe of my text) I laid down this as a <hi>Second</hi> truth to be proved, that <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and ſuch like outward ſervices, did tend to keep men from ſin, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance juſtice, charity and piety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. And firſt it ſeems to me as though there was the very ſpirit and reaſon of theſe three things in the threefold ſacrifices that were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Their <hi>ſin-offerings</hi> which were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106191:59"/>withall, may be looked upon as a piece of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and to be given by way of ſatisfaction unto God for the offences and wrongs done unto him. And the <hi>peace-offerings,</hi> as a piece of love and gratitude to God the author of all <hi>Mercies:</hi> and as a peice of charity and kindneſs to the poor, who in many caſes were parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of them. And then their whole <hi>burnt-offerings</hi> were tokens of their obedience, and <hi>humble</hi> acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he was their great <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord</hi> of whom they held the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and from whom they received whatſoever they did enjoy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And ſo <hi>Secondly</hi> their Sacrifices taught them to conſider that they ſhould conſecrate and offer themſelves unto him, ſeeing that <hi>they</hi> were his, no leſs then their ſheep or calves which they brought to his Altar. Theſe ſacrifices being their <hi>tribute</hi> which they paid to their ſupream Lord, did expreſs that they were tyed to him in any <hi>ſervices</hi> that he would require of them. They could not think that he would be pleaſed with
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106191:59"/>an <hi>Ox,</hi> more then with a <hi>man,</hi> and that he would hold them excuſed if they rebelled againſt <hi>him,</hi> to whom they made theſe conſtant acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments. They did not hereby pay their debts, but confeſs that they were indebted: They were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by theſe from all obligations, but teſtified a ſenſe that they and all theirs were engaged to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> they promoted true holineſs as they ſhewed the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of ſin, and the guilt which it brought upon thoſe that did commit it. For what need was there that theſe poor creatures ſhould ſuffer for their faults, if God was not much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by their diſobedience? The cries and ſtruglings of the beaſts might put them in mind what neceſſity ſin brought upon them of ſuffering, and how cruelly it would uſe thoſe who continued in it. And it would be eaſie to ſhew, that there was no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment threatned for the breach of any of the <hi>ten commandments,</hi> whether <hi>ſtoning,</hi> or <hi>ſtrangulation,</hi> or <hi>cutting of the throat,</hi> or <hi>burning</hi> (for there were
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106191:60"/>but theſe <hi>four</hi>) but it was repreſented in the death of theſe beaſts, which were thrown on the pavement, tyed about the throat, ſlain and burned ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in whole or in part upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And <hi>fourthly</hi> theſe Sacrifices and all other outward ceremonies might well teach them how far they ought to keep from all inward difilements, who were to be ſo remote from all fleſhly pollutions. They that were under ſuch a conſtant diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of God, and taught by ſuch holy men, could not whithout a ſtrange neglect be ſo ſottiſhly ſtupid as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God took no care of the <hi>ſoul,</hi> who would have the <hi>body</hi> ſo clean and pure. If a beaſt muſt not have any blemiſh in it, nor the man that offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it any legal uncleaneſs upon him: he might eaſily think that God expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted his mind ſhould be holy, and not in a worſe condition then his beaſt or his body. If they were to waſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their ſacrifices, then the ſoul ſure was not to be dirty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure. If they were to be ſeperated
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106191:60"/>from all unclean perſons, then much more from bad company. And if they might not ſo much as eat with a Gentile, then much leſs might they partake with them in their ſins and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud Photium in Biblioth. pag.</hi> 887.</note> I know not what truth there is in the obſervation of <hi>Eulogius;</hi> but he wonders why there being ſo many clean creatures allowed by God to be eaten in the Law, there were only five, (<hi>viz.</hi> a Goat, a Sheep, an Ox a Turtle and a Pigeon) which were uſed in ſacrifices; unleſs it had an aenigmatical and figurative meaning, to denote our <hi>five ſenſes,</hi> which we are to purifie and cleanſe, that we may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to God, and be fit to draw near unto him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And therefore <hi>fifthly</hi> we may look upon the law of ceremonies as an hedge to the Law of moral precepts,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or the <hi>ten commandments.</hi> Some things as <hi>Ariſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> well obſerves, are good in themſelves and to be beloved <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for their own ſakes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 1 <hi>Ethic.</hi>
                  </note> and others are good and lovely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the ſake of the former; as they are either <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> effective and operative of them,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106191:61"/>or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in ſome ſort a preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and guard to them; or as they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hindrances of their contraries, and forbid that which would deſtroy them. Now though the things that we are ſpeaking of were not good in themſelves, nor had any proper worth in them, as <hi>juſtice, mercy,</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> have: yet they were of this latter ſort of goods, and ſerved to maintain theſe greater things in their ſacredneſs, and to prohibit them from infringing any of the rights belonging unto them. God kept the Iſraelites at a great diſtance from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating theſe commands, by making them obſervant of leſſer injunctions. Their fear of theſe meaner offences was intended as a guard and ſecurity to the greater ſanctions and commands. As a man that dare not leap over an hedge into our paſture, will not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture one would think to climb over the wall into our garden: ſo he that durſt not break through and tranſgreſs the bounds of theſe outward precepts; it was to be preſumed would never be ſo bold as to tread under feet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106191:61"/>the more divine Laws. God intended mainly to preſerve the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>moral</hi> laws and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts: and ſo he ſet the <hi>ceremonial</hi> as a thornie fence about them, to keep them from being broken. Their not eating of blood muſt needs make them to have a natural abhorrence of murder (<hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4, 5.) and their not marrying within ſuch degrees of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity, was an exerciſe of their <hi>chaſtity,</hi> and a great ſecurity againſt adultery and ſuch like wickedneſs. Their taking no uſe of their <hi>poor</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and leaving them the corners of the fields when they reaped, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was a means to make them <hi>not to covet</hi> nor be greedy of the world. Their obſerving of ſo many daies in memory of Gods mercies, muſt needs teach them to have the <hi>Sabbath</hi> in great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, which was in memory of the creation of the world, and their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Seeing they muſt break down ſo many mounds and banks as were caſt up about the eternal Law: it might reaſonably be ſuppoſed that they would never attempt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106191:62"/>it, at leaſt not as long as they kept theſe entire.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And in particular theſe things kept them from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which was the higheſt contempt of God that could be.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orat.</hi> 42.</note> They were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſaith of the whole Law) a <hi>wall ſet up between God and Idols,</hi> to keep them from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto ſtrange worſhip: A parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they muſt break down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they and the Gods of the heathens could meet together. And this <hi>Maimon</hi> doth conceive to be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe precepts which carry not their reaſon in themſelves: that God might make them abhor to participate in the Religion of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that were about them. For he well obſerves, that God commands them ſuch things as were quite contrary to their practice: ſo that what the heathens loved, that they were to abominate: and what they reverenced, the Jews were to have for daily uſe; and they were not ſo much as to worſhip toward the ſame quarter of heaven; but
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106191:62"/>whereas the world generally had their holy place in the Eaſt, God placed his ſanctuary in the Weſt. But it is not his obſervation alone; for <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> long before in his diſputation with the <hi>Jew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dialog, cum Tryph.</note> ſaith that the Iſraelites making a golden calf and offering ſacrifice to it after the manner of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> God did accommodate himſelf to them, and commanded them to offer him ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that ſo they might not give away his worſhip unto Idols. And more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his anſwers <hi>ad Orthodoxos</hi> (if that book be his) he ſaith that the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans taking all living creatures (except a Swine) to have ſomething of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reſponſ.</hi> 35. <hi>ad Orthod.</hi>
                  </note> God diſtinguiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the clean and unclean, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the one to be offered in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but the other he forbad to be ſo much as eaten; By both ſhewing that they were unworthy of the honour or name of gods, which might either be ſlain and eaten, or elſe were to be reputed of as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Theodoret</hi> aſſerts it ſtill more particularly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>de curat. Graec. affect.</hi>
                  </note> that the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106191:63"/>a <hi>Goat</hi> and a <hi>Sheep,</hi> as well as a <hi>Calf</hi> or <hi>Heifer:</hi> and likewiſe hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Turtle</hi> and <hi>Pigeon</hi> among the birds in greateſt veneration; God commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ſacrifice theſe rather then any other, that ſo they might learn how vile the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe people was, whoſe gods were continually ſlain and eaten by them. And for this cauſe alſo it was (as he thinks) that God would not let them eat Swines fleſh, becauſe the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> abſtaining from the reſt as gods, did think it lawfull to eat of this crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only. But if it ſhould be thought that the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> did not worſhip a <hi>Goat,</hi> as it is certain they did a <hi>Cow,</hi> yet the Jews confeſs that the <hi>Zabii</hi> or <hi>Sabaeans</hi> who were their near neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, did give divine honour to it, and againſt their infection they were no leſs to receive an Antidote then againſt the other. And this perhaps may be the reaſon why God loaded them with ſuch a world of ceremonies, that they might be ſo conſtantly imployed, as not to have time to think of adding
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106191:63"/>any other devices of their own or others to his ſervice, having enough to do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Only his infinite. Wiſdom made theſe things ſerve to teach them higher duties, and to be ſhadows alſo of moſt glorious things to come, which I am not now to treat of.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But <hi>ſeventhly,</hi> as they put them in mind to conſecrate themſelves to God, ſo they remembred them to give him the very beſt, and the ſecrets of their ſouls. For it is well obſerved by <hi>Cyril Alex.</hi> that though God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them to offer ſacrifices as other Nations did, yet not after their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but ſo artificially and skilfully or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that (as I juſt now ſaid) they did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> travel with the form of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and intellectual worſhip in their womb,
<note place="margin">L. 9. <hi>Contra Julianum.</hi>
                  </note> of which they are now at laſt delivered. Their whole <hi>burnt offerings</hi> which aſcended intirely to heaven, and were to be choſen out of the beſt of their beaſts, fruits or liquors, might well carry along with them the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of their thoughts and affections, yea their whole ſouls toward God,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106191:64"/>in whoſe ſervice they were to ſpend themſelves. And when they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed <hi>peace offerings,</hi> they were to give to God the <hi>kidneyes</hi> or <hi>reins,</hi> which are the ſeat of carnal pleaſure; and the <hi>heart</hi> (as ſome think) which is the fountain of all living motions, and the ſeat (in the ancient language) of the thoughts; and then the <hi>blood</hi> of the beaſt, which might well teach them to offer even their lives to him (who gave life to them) as well as all other things which were moſt dear in their eyes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To which it may be added, that the ſacrifices could not be accepted, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>perſon</hi> as well as the beaſt which he brought were clean and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. So that the offering did not make him good, but ſuppoſed him to be ſo already. <hi>Plutarch</hi> gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how exact the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were about the red Cow which they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed was to be offered to <hi>Typhon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. de Iſid. &amp; Oſir.</note> when he ſayes that if there were but one hair black or white, ſhe was judged to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> unlawfull to be offered in ſacrifice. But he tells us likewiſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106191:64"/>(in the ſame place) that the perſon who brought it was to be ſound and in a good ſtate of health; for they thought that that being which is moſt pure, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled and without blemiſh, ought not to be ſerved <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, with bodies or ſouls that were full of putrifying ſores or diſeaſes. You cannot think that the Jews were no leſs intelligent then theſe heathen; eſpecially ſince God required of the man that offered them, that he ſhould be ſo far from greater pollutions, that he ſhould not lie ſo much as under any ceremonial defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Or if there were any ſecret naughtineſs lying in his heart while his outward actions were unbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mable, yet the ſacrifice of ſuch a wicked man was an abomination to the Lord, who knows the heart, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may obſerve that after the Pſalmiſt had ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Lord are a broken Spirit, &amp;c.</hi> and deſired acceptance with God for him and his people, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. he adds, <hi>Then ſhalt thou be pleaſed with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of righteouſneſs, with burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:106191:65"/>&amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. As if he had told us <hi>firſt,</hi> that a broken and contrite heart muſt go before, elſe no ſacrifices could be accepted to do the ſoul good; and then <hi>ſecondly,</hi> that in the time of offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they muſt be accompanied with <hi>righteouſneſs, i.e.</hi> the mans ſoul muſt be holy and devout, and have a good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in it unto God.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And after this they could not be accepted but by the mediation of the Prieſt, which taught them <hi>great humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> even when they were at the beſt, and in the greateſt purity of body and ſoul.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And again there were ſome ſins for which no ſacrifices would be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, nor no Prieſt could intercede; which both taught them humbly to wait on the mercy of God, that he would find out a ſacrifice and a Prieſt to expiate them; and likewiſe to take great heed how they fell into thoſe ſins.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And the <hi>ſacrifices</hi> themſelves are to be conſidered as a part of their <hi>civil righteouſneſs;</hi> for by the giving of theſe to God, and obſerving the reſt of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106191:65"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> his Laws they had a title to the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> If they kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from defilements, or brought theſe oblations, and obſerved the feaſts, and kept the outward part of the ten commandments, they were ſaved from being cut off by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or caſt out by God from the poſſeſſions that he had given them. But God did not intend that this ſhould make citizens of heaven, or give them a right to the celeſtiall inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; <hi>Canaan</hi> it ſelf being but a type of heaven, and theſe ritual obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but ſhadows of more heavenly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, whereby they were to ſeek that better countrey.</p>
               <p n="12">12. And yet when they performed theſe acts with an holy heart, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods command, and as a part of his will: not relying on them, nor contenting themſelves with them alone: they might be accepted as a piece of diviner righteouſneſs, as <hi>Iſaacs</hi> offering his ſon was, meerly becauſe God required him ſo to do. For then they were converted to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of ſpirituality in them: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:106191:66"/>of another nature: Then he that calls himſelf the <hi>righteous Lord,</hi> and the <hi>holy one of</hi> Iſrael, ſtiles himſelf alſo by this name, <hi>The Lord, whoſe fire is in</hi> Zion, <hi>and his furnace in Jeruſalem,</hi> Iſa. 31.9. Thoſe divine Acts which render us acceptable in Gods ſight might be imployed in theſe things as well as in others, that faith, obedience, reſignation, humility, liberality, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which God requires, might be exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe obſervances, as well as in another matter; and for them (not meerly for the ſacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) they were commended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:106191:66"/>
               <p>AND now how well will all this pains be beſtowed, if every man who reads theſe things will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himſelf, nor be at reſt without a ſtate of inward purity and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the divine will, and a ſincere obedience to every part of that Law which our Lord hath given us! Do not I beſeech you cover your ſelves with the leaves of piety, nor ſhroud your ſelves under the empty ſhadows of Religion: but put on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, bring forth the reall fruits of juſtice, mercy, and humble godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; let the life of God poſſeſs your ſouls, and the divine ſpirit actuate and inform you as living members of his body. We have our <hi>waſhings,</hi> and our <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> and our <hi>dayes</hi> of reſt as well as the Jews had: let us have a care that we uſe them out of a ſenſe of that duty we owe to God, and as means to exerciſe and increaſe our graces; and not pride our ſelves as they did in outward performances, and an heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſanctity. If we glory meerly in
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:106191:67"/>our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> in our being of ſuch a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and perſwaſion, in going to our Churches, hearing of Sermons there, and repeating them at home, receiving of the Sacrament of Chriſts body and blood, praying, ſinging Pſalms, and offering praiſes: We do but mock God with outward ſhews, and bring him to an Idol as <hi>Michal</hi> did <hi>Sauls</hi> meſſengers inſtead of a man. Nay, it is a greater ſhame and more damning for us to miſtake ſo groſly and to think to pleaſe God with ſuch trivial things as words and outward geſtures, when we know more then they did, and have <hi>their</hi> miſcarriages laid ſo plainly before us. If God did not only deſpiſe but hate the Jewiſh ſervice when not joyned with obedience to his eternal precepts, then much more will he loth all ungodly men now with all their worſhip which they bring him, though never ſo pompous and ceremonious. For their Religion was full of ſhadows, ceremonies and outward ſigns, but ours is a Religion of more ſimplicity, and therefore we can be the leſs temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to formality. And beſides we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:106191:67"/>eaſed of that burden, of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy yoke which lay upon their necks, the heartier obedience in other things may be more juſtly exacted of us, and expected from us. Let me conclude therefore with the words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of us Gentiles, and <hi>beſeech you by the mercies of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1, 2.</note> that ye preſent your bodies a living ſacrifice, holy, acceptable unto God, which is your reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And be not conformed to this world, but be ye transformed by the renewing of your mind, that ye may prove what is that good, acceptable and perfect will of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
